<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The hystorie of the seven wise maisters of Rome]</title>
            <title>Seven sages of Rome. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15582</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23250584</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178576</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248530503</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21299.7</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S2303</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The hystorie of the seven wise maisters of Rome]</title>
                  <title>Seven sages of Rome. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>[Now newlye corrected</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[230+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Purfoot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1602]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.p. lacking; title suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Edition statement suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Publisher and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: signatures A-A₈, I₆ and all after Q₃ lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178576:1"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>conceiue. Then when she heard that the Emperour had a Son with sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wise Maisters to be tostered and taught to the behoofe and profite of the Empire, shee thought in her selfe, and wished his death. And from that howe foorth, shee imagined how she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conspire his destruction. It happened on a night as the Emperor lay in his bed, he said to the Empres: My most deere &amp; best beloued wife, I shall now shew &amp; open to you the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of my heart, for vnder the Sun is ther no creature that I loue so well as you, and therfore trust in my loue. Then said the saire noble Empresse, if it be so as you say, I require of you one little boone or petition. Desire what you will sayde the Emperour, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd all that to me is possible, I shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>till and giue it to you. Then sayd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Empresse, my right deere Lord, as you know I haue no child by you yet conceiued, wherefore I am sore
<pb facs="tcp:178576:2"/> pensiue and heauie, but it is shewed me that ye haue one Sonne only, the which is set to the Seuen wise Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters to be taught and gouerned, and him hold I and repute for mine owne Sonne, wherfore I beseech you that yee will send for him that I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> see him and haue consolation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, as though he were mine owne Hereupon answered the Emperour it is sixteene yeeres past since that I saw him, your will be fulfilled. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent the Emperor sent vnto the seuen Maisters a Letter sealed with his secret signet, that vpon paine of death they should bring his Sonne in the Feast of Pentecost or Whitson<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide then next following.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Seuen wise Maisters after the sight of the Emperors letter, wold fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> see the course of the Firmament an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Planets, whether it were good to obay his commaundement, or not.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:2"/>
               <p>And as the Maisters the letter had read, and had vnderstood the will of the Emperour; in the night they went and beheld the starres of the Firmament, whether it should be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to take their iourney with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Child after the Emperours will, or not: and they sawe clearely in the Starres, that if they should leade the Childe in that time assigned. At the first word that he should speake he should die an euill Death: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were all right sorrye, and as they beheld another Starre, they sawe, that if they deliuered not the Childe at the day aforesayd, they should loose their heads. Then said one of them, of two euils the least is to be chosen; it is better that all wee die, than that the Child should loose his life, therefore that we may saue the childs life, let vs go to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. And as they were thus sorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the Child came downe from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:3"/> Chamber, and seeing his Masters so heauy, he demaunded then the cause of their heauinesse; whereupon they answered: Sir, we haue receued your Fathers Letters, vpon pain of death that now in this high Feast of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecost wee should leade you to your Countrey, wherupon we haue behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Firmament, wherin we clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see and finde, that if we within the time before prefixed present you to your Father, At the first word that ye shall pronounce out of your mouth, ye shall bee to the most vilest death con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Then said the Child, I must also behold the Firmament with the Stars, and so he did, and found clere in a little starre, that if hee could ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine from speaking seauen days, he should be preserued, and saue his life. And after he had seene this, he called his Maisters, and shewed them the Star, and sayd, behold my deere ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sters, I see perfectly in the starre th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:3"/> if I abstaine my selfe by the space of vii. dayes I shall saue my life. Ye are now vii. Masters the wisest of all the world, it is a little thing to you, that euery of you for mee one day doe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere, and with your wise answere, euery of you his day my life may saue and keep, &amp; I in the 8. day shall speak for my selfe, and shall saue my life, and all you from perill. As the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters had beholden that certen starre, they iudged in them, that the Child had sayd troth, saying, almighty God bee thanked, that the wisedome and cunning of our Disciple exceedeth vs all. Then said the first Maister <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillas,</hi> Lord I shall speake for you the first day and saue your life. And <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulus</hi> the second Maister said, I shall for you the second day answere: and so consequently euery of them promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to answere for him his day. And this sayd, they cloathed the Child in purple, &amp; leapt to horsebacke with a
<pb facs="tcp:178576:4"/> faire companie, and hasted them with the Child to the Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Emperour rode to meete his Sonne comming from his Study, with pompe and pride.</head>
               <p>WHen the Emperor perceiued that his Sonne was comming vppon the way, hee rode with great ioy to meet him. The Masters vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the comming of the Emperour, said vnto the Child, it is best that we depart, that in the meane while wee may prouide howe wee may saue your life. The Child said, it pleaseth me that you do so, but haue mind on mee in time of my necessitie: so they tooke their leaue, and departed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Cittie, and the Child came after accompanied most honourably. And as hee &amp; his Father the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour were mette, for ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he tooke him about the necke and kissed him and said, my deer son, how
<pb facs="tcp:178576:4"/> is it with you, it is long since that I saw you, he bowed downe his head and answered nothing: the Father had great wonder why that he spake not, and thought in himselfe that his Maisters had him so informed, that he riding should not speak. And when they were come into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pallace, and were descended from their horses, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Father tooke the Son by the hand, and led him into the Hal, and set him next him and beheld him, and sayd: tell me how it is with your Masters, and how they haue infourmed you, for now are many yeeres past since I saw you? he enclyned down his head and gaue no answere: the Father sayd, wherefore speake ye not to me? And when the Empresse heard that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperors son was come, shee was right ioyous and glad, &amp; sayd, I will goe see him: shee apparelled her with rich attire, and tooke with her twoo of her Gentlewomen, &amp; went there
<pb facs="tcp:178576:5"/> as the Emperour was sitting with his Sonne, and sate her down by the Child, and she sayd to the Emperour, is this your Son that hath been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished with the seuen wise Masters? and he sayd, it is my son but he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not: she sayd, deliuer to mee your Sonne, and if euer he speake, I shall make him to speak: then said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, rise and go with her; the Son did reuerence to the father, as though he sayd, I am ready to accomplish your will; and so went with her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Empres led <hi>Dioclesian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Son with her into her cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for to make good cheere with him, the which he withstood.</head>
               <p>THe Empresse led him with her into her chamber, &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all other to avoide, &amp; set him by her afore her bed, and said, O my best beloued <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> I haue heard much of your person and beautie, but now I am glad that I may see that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:5"/> with mine eyes that my heart coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth &amp; loueth; for I haue caused your Father to send for you, that I might haue solace and ioy of your Person. Wherefore I without fault giue you knowledge, that I for your loue, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day haue kept my Virginitie? speake to mee, and let vs goe to bed togither: but he gaue her no answere. She seeing that, sayd to him, O good <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> which hast the halfe of my soule, why speake you not to me, or at the least shew me some token of loue? what shall I doe, speake to me I am ready to fulfill and performe your wil? and when she had thus said she embraced him, and would haue kissed his mouth, and he turned his visage from her, and in no wise would consent: then said she againe to him, O Son wherefore doe ye thus with me, let vs sleep together, and then shal ye well perceiue, that for your loue I
<pb facs="tcp:178576:6"/> haue kept my Virginitie: and he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his visage frō her. She seeing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was of her ashamed, shewed vnto him her naked body and breasts, and said, Behold my Son, what body I haue, is at your wil, giue me your cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, or else it shall be hard for mee to depart hence with my right mind: he neither with signe, nor with counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of visage shewed her any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of loue, but as much as hee could, withdrew himselfe from her. When shee saw that, shee sayd, O my most sweet Sonne, if it please not you to consent to me, ne yet speak, perhaps for some reasonable cause, lo heere is paper, pen, and inke, then write your will, whether I maye at any time hereafter trust in your loue, or not. The Child wrote as hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: O Lady, God forbid that I should defile my Fathers Orchard, for I wote not what fruite I should haue of it, I knowe well one thing,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:6"/> that I should sin in the sight of God, and also run in the malediction of my Father, and therfore from henceforth prouoke and stirre me no more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. When she had seen and read the writing, shee tare it with her teeth, and rent her cloathes to her nauill, and all to scratched her Visage, vntill it was all bloudie, and cast from her all the ornaments of her head, and cryed with a loud voice, come hither my Lords and helpe mee, least that this rude and euill bodie shame and rauish mee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the Empresse complained to the Emperour, of the shame done to her by his Sonne.</head>
               <p>THe Emperour was in the Hall, and hearing the noise and cry of the Empresse, he hastily ran to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his chamber with his Knights and other of his Seruants follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, for to see what was the matter. Then beganne the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb facs="tcp:178576:7"/> to cry, and to speak to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour in this case: O my Lord, haue pittie and compassion vpon mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, this young man is not your Sonne, but the foulest Ribaud &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot that euer was borne, and a defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of women: for as you know well, I led and brought him with me into my chamber, and would haue exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and caused him to haue spoken. I haue doone as much thereto as I can, or may; and whiles I with my words exhorted and mooued him for to haue spoken, he hath endeauoured himselfe with me to haue sinned, and because I would not to him consent, but withstoode as much as I might for to flye the shame, hee hath made my Visage all bloudy, and hath all to torne my Vesture, and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my head, as you may open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see, and if yee had not so soone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome vnto my calling, he had accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished in mee his most foule and
<pb facs="tcp:178576:7"/> wicked appetite. When the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour saw and heard this, filled with great malice and woodnesse, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded his Seruants that they should lead him to the Gallowes, and hang him. And when his Lords hard thereof, they sayd, Lord you haue no more but this Sonne onely, it is not good that yee thus lightly put him to death: the law is ordained for trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressors and misdoers, and if it be so that he must die, let him by the Law die, least that it be sayd, that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour in his great furie and yre, without Law and Iustice, hath put his onely Sonne to Death. As the Emperour heard this, he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to be put in Prison vntill the time that Iudgement were giuen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. And when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse vnderstoode that the Childe was not put to Death, shee cried and weeped bitterly, and would haue no rest: when the night was come,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:8"/> the Emperor entred into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to go to bed, and found his wife weeping and sorrowing, to whome he sayd: O my most deere Ladie, for what cause are ye sorrowfull? shee answered, know you not, how that your accursed Sonne hath done mee so much shame, &amp; so dishonoured you, that ye haue commaunded him to bee hanged, and yet he liueth, and your word is not perfourmed, neither is my shame reuenged. To morow said the Emperor he shall die by the law: then said shee, shall hee so long liue? then might it happen to you, as it did to a Burgesse of Roome, of whome an example is mentioned: the Emperor sayd, I pray you shew me that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: that shall I do gladly sayde the Empresse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The first Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>IN the Cittie of Rome was a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesse, the which had a faire Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:8"/> wherein hee had standing a noble Tree, the which euerie yeare brought forth fruite of great vertue, for whosoeuer eate thereof that were sicke of any manner of sicknesse, as of Leaprosie, or of any other, he should soon be whole and receiue his health. It happened vppon a day as the Burgesse went into his Gardaine to visite and see the Tree, hee espyed vnder the Tree a faire young Impe, and called to him the Gardiner, and sayd: My friend of his young impe I giue thee charge, for I trust of that to plant a better Tree than this is: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gardiner sayd, I shall it gladly doe. Another time the Burgesse came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into his Gardaine to visite this young Plant, and ii appeared vnto him that it grewe not so much as it should doe, and hee sayd vnto the Gardiner, how may this be? and he sayd, it is no woonder, for this great Tree hath so great armes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178576:9"/> braunches, that the ayre may not come to the roote of the yong Tree: then said the Burgesse, cut and hewe off the armes and the boughes, that the aire may come thereto, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dener did as hee was commaunded. The Burges came again at another time for to see this young plant, and thought that it grew neuer the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and said to the Gardener, what is it that letteth this Plant to growe now? And then he sayd, I suppose y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> height of the old tree letteth the sun, that the raine may not come thereto, and therefore it cannot grow. Then sayde the Maister vnto him, hewe downe the Tree by the ground, for I hope of this plant to haue a better than euer that was. The Gardener hearing his Maister, obayed him, and hewed downe the Tree, and as soone as this was done, the young Plant all wholly perished, and came to naught, whereof there came great
<pb facs="tcp:178576:9"/> harme: for when the poore and sicke people perceiued that the Tree was so destroyed, they cursed all them that were Councellors and helpers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the which they all aforetime were healed and cured of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and maledies. Then sayd the Empresse vnderstād ye what I haue sayd? He answered, yea, right well: then said she, I shal declare to you the meaning of that which I haue sayd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Declaration of the Example.</head>
               <p>THis Tree, my Lord, betokeneth your most noble Person, how that with your councell and helpe, many poore and sicke folke are greatly hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and comforted. And the young Impe which is growen vnder the great Tree, is your cursed Sonne, that nowe by his cunning beginneth to growe, and studieth how hee first may cut off the armes and boughs of your might, &amp; how to win to him the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:10"/> land and fauor of the people, yea and more vnnaturally, he imagineth to destroy your person, that he may him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe raigne, but what shall then ensue thereof? all poore and feeble people shall curse all them, who might haue destroyed your Sonne, and haue not done it, therefore I councell you whylest you are in your power, and liuing, that ye destroy him, least that the curse of the people fall vppon you. Then sayd the Emperour, yee haue giuen me good councell, to morrow I shall condemne him to the most vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest death that can be thought. When the daye was come, the Emperour went and sate in iudgement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded his Seruants that they should lead his son to be hanged with trumpet sounding in token of death. And as the Emperors Son was led through the Cittie, the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple beganne to weepe and crye, Alas the onely Son of the Emperor is led
<pb facs="tcp:178576:10"/> towards his death, and therewithall came <hi>Pantillas</hi> the first Maister ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vppon a Horse: When the Child sawe him, he bowed his head to him, as though hee had sayd, haue minde vpon me when you come before my Father, see how I am ledde towards the Gallowes: then the Maister said to the seruants, make no hast, for I hope by the grace of god this day to deliuer him from the death: then said all the people, O good Maister hast you to the Palace, &amp; saue your Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple: hee smote the horse with his spurs till he came to the Pallace, and kneeled before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperour and did him reuerēce. To whome y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperor sayd, it shall neuer bee to thee good, who answered, I haue deserued a better reward: the Emperour sayd there thou lyest, for I deliuered him to thee in all things well mannered, and now he is dumme, and that worse is, hee would haue oppressed my Wife,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:11"/> therfore this day hee shall die, and ye all shall die a shamefull death. The Maister sayd, O Lord, as for your sonne, for so much as he speaketh not, the cause thereof God knoweth, and without cause it is not, as ye shall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand: and where you say that he would haue defiled your Empresse, I shall say to you of a troth, he hath beene in our companie by the space of 16. yeres, and we neuer could perceiue such abuse by him. And therefore my deere Lord I shall shew you one thing, that if you put your Sonne to death for the wordes of your Wife, it should happen to you worse than to a Knight, the which killed his best Greyhound through the wordes of his wife, which saued his Son from the Death: then sayd the Emperour to the Maister, tell me that example. The Master sayd, Lord that shall I not doe, for before I should make an end therof, your sonne might be dead,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:11"/> and then in vaine and without fruite should I rehearse it: but if it pleaseth you this notable example to heare, call againe your Son till to morrow, and as ye thinke by reason, then doe with him your pleasure. As the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour heard that, anon he willed the Child to be called againe, and in the mean time he set him in prison whiles the Maister should finish his tale, and then hee began to say in this manner as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the first Maister.</head>
               <p>THere was a valiant Knight, which had one onely Sonn, as you haue, the which hee loued so much, that he ordained for his kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping three Nourishers: The first should giue him sucke and feede him, the second should wash him and keep him cleane, and the third should bring him to sleepe and rest. This Knight had also a Greyhound and a Fawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:12"/> which he also loued right well, The Greyhound was so good, that he neuer ranne at any game, but hee tooke it, and held it till his Maister came. And if his Maister disposed him to go vnto a battaile, if he should not speed in the Battaile, anon as he should amount vppon his horse, the Greyhounde would take the Horse tayle in his mouth, and drawe backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and would also crie and howle maruailously loud. By these signes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knight vnderstood whether he should speede in his Iourney, or not. The Faulcon was so Gentle and so hardy that he was neuer cast off his prey, but he tooke it.</p>
               <p>The same Knight had great plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in Iusting and Tourney, so that vpon a time vnder his Castle hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed a Turnament, to the which came many good Lords &amp; Knightes. The Knight entred into the Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and his Ladye went with her
<pb facs="tcp:178576:12"/> maydens to see it, and as they went out, after went the Nourishers, and left the Child lying there alone in the Cradle in the Hall, where the Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounde laye nigh the wall, and the Hauke or Fawlcon standing vpon a Perch. In this Hall there was a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent lurking or hidde in a hole to al them of the Castle vnknowne, the which when he perceiued that they were all absent, hee put his head out of his hole, and when he sawe none but the Childe lying in the Cradle, he went out of his hole towardes the Cradle for to haue slayne the Child. The noble Fawlcon perceiuing that and beholding the Greyhound that was sleeping, made such a noyse and rustling with her winges present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Greyhounde awooke and arose vp, and when hee sawe the Serpent nigh the Childe, anone against him he leapt, and they both fought so long together, vntill that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:13"/> the Serpēt had greeuously hurt and wounded the Greyhound, that hee bled so sore, that the earth about the Cradle was all bloudie. The Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound when that he felt himselfe so greeuously wounded and hurt, start fiercely vppon the Serpent &amp; fought so sore together and so eagerly, that between them the Cradle was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tost with the Child, the bottome vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And because that the Cradle had foure Pomels like feete, falling towardes the earth, they saued the Childs life, and his visage from any hurting, what shall I saye more? Incontinent thereafter, with great paine the Greyhound ouercame and slue the Serpent, &amp; went &amp; layd him downe againe in his place, and licked his wounds.</p>
               <p>And anone after as the Iusts and Tourney was done, the Nourishers were the first that came into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, and as they saw the Cradle tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:178576:13"/> vpside downe on the earth c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> passed round about with bloud, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that the Greyhound was also bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, they thought and sayd amongest themselues that the Greyhounde had slayne the Childe, and were not so wise as to turne vp the Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle againe with the Childe, for to haue seene what was thereof befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len. But they sayd, let vs flye or run away, least that our Maister put or lay the blame vpon vs, and slay vs. As they were thus running away, they met with the Knights wife, and she sayd to them, wherefore make ye this sorrow, and whither will ye run? then sayd they, O Lady, woe and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe be to vs and to you, why sayd shee, what is there happened, shewe me? the Greyhound, they sayd, that our Lord &amp; Master loueth so much, hath deuoured and slayne your Son, and lieth by the wall all full of the bloud. As the Ladie heard this, she
<pb facs="tcp:178576:14"/> fell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the earth and beganne to weep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> crye pitiously, and sayd, alas O my deere Sonne be ye thus slaine and dead, what shall I nowe doe that I haue mine onely Sonne thus lost? herewithall came in the Knight from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Tourney, and beholding his Ladie thus crying and making sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, hee demaunded other where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shee made so great sorrowe and lamentation? She answered him, O my Lorde, your Greyhounde that ye loue so much, hath slaine your onely Sonne, and lyeth by the wall sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate with the bloud of the Childe. The Knight vehemently angred, went into the Hall, and the Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound went to meete him, and did fawne as hee was woont to doe, and the Knight drewe out his Sword and with one stroake smote off the Greyhounds head, and then went to the Cradle &amp; found his son all whole, and by the Cradle the Serpent slain,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:14"/> and then by diuers signes hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that the Greyhound had fought against the Serpent for the defence of the Child. Then with great sorrow and weeping hee tare his haire, and said, wo be to me, that for the words of my Wife, I haue slayne my good Greyhound, the which hath saued my Childes life, and hath slaine the Serpent: therefore I will put my selfe to pennance, and so hee brake his Sword in three peeces, and wēt towards the holy Land, and abode there all the dayes of his life. Then sayd the Maister to the Emperour, Lorde vnderstand yee what I haue said, and he answered and sayd, right well. The Maister sayd if that ye do put your Son to death for the words of your Wife, it shall happen to you, worse than it did to the knight for his Greyhound. The Emperour sayd, ye haue shewed me a faire example, and without doubt this day my Sonne
<pb facs="tcp:178576:15"/> shall not die: then said the Maister, if ye do fo, ye do wisely, and I thanke you that ye haue spared him this day for my sake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Second Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>WHen that the Empresse heard that the child was not yet dead, shee began to weepe bitterly, and sate her downe on the earth in ashes, and would not lift vp her head: as the Emperour heard that, he entred into the Chamber and said to her, O good wife, wherefore make ye all this sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp; trouble your selfe so much: she sayd, aske you that of me? know you not well what great despight &amp; shame I haue suffered of your vnhappy son? and how ye haue promised mee that you would see Iustice to be therefore executed on him, &amp; yet he liueth? Of troth it shall happen to you as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to a shepheard &amp; a Bore. The Emperour sayd, I pray you shew me
<pb facs="tcp:178576:15"/> that example for my learning: shee sayd, as yesterday I shewed one and saw no good effect that came thereof, to what intent should I now doe the like? Neuerthelesse, I shall declare this notable example vnto you, as hereafter you shall heare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Second Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>THere was sometime an Emperour the which hadde a great Forrest, wherein was a Bore which was so cruell and so fell, that men going through the Forrest, he killed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured. The Emperour being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore right heauie, proclaimed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout all his Dominions, that whatsoeuer hee was that could slay the Bore, shoulde haue his onely Daughter to Wife, and thereto his Empire after his death: and as this was in all places proclaymed, there was not one man found that durste giue the aduenture: but there was
<pb facs="tcp:178576:16"/> a Shepheard, who thought in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, might I this Bore ouercome and slay, I should not onely aduance my selfe, but also all my generation and kindred. So he tooke his shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heardes staffe in his hand and went to the Forrest. And as the Bore had of him a sight, hee drewe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the heardesman, and he for feare clymed vpon a Tree, then the Bore beganne to bite and gnawe the tree, so that the heard thought short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that hee should haue ouerthrowne it. This Tree was laden with great plentie of fruite, the Heard gathered and plucked thereof, and cast them to the Bore, insomuch that when hee was filled therewith, he layd him downe to sleepe, the which the heard perceiuing, by little and little descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Tree, and with the one hand he clawed the Bore, and with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther held himselfe vpon the Tree, &amp; seeing that the Bore slept very sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:16"/> hee drewe out his knife and smote the Bore to the heart and killed him, and so consequently wedded the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Daughter to his Wife, and after the death of her Father, he was made Emperor: then said she my lord wot ye not what I haue sayd, he said, right well. Then said she, this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Bore betokeneth your most Noble Person, against whome may no man withstand, neyther by wisedome, nor with strength. This shepheard with his staffe, is the Person of your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious Sonne who with his staffe of cunning beginneth to play with you as the Heardsman clawed the Bore, and made him to sleepe, and after killed him: in the same ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Maisters of your Sonne by their false Fables &amp; narrations clawe you &amp; glose with you, vntill the time that your Sonne slay you, that hee may raigne. Then said the Emperor, God forbid that they should do to me
<pb facs="tcp:178576:17"/> as hee did to the Bore, and sayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, this day my Sonne shall die, and shee answered, if ye doe so, then you doe wisely. Then the Emperour the second time sitting in iudgement, commaunded to lead him to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes and hange him, and whilest he was going, the second Maister came before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperour doing him reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, as before is shewed in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the first Maister, to whome the second Master sayd, O my Lord Emperour, if you should so slay your Sonne for the words of your wife, it might worse come to you, than it did to a Knight which for the words of his Wife, was vniustly put vppon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pillorie: the Emperour said, O good Master tell me how that happened, &amp; he said, My Lord I shall not say it, vnlesse you will call your Sonne from the death vntill the time that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> example bee tould, the which if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> turne you not from your purpose <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:17"/> thē let your wil be fulfilled. Then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Emperor Cōmanded that the Child should be called backe once againe. And vnder this manner that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the second Maister began to tell</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the second Maister.</head>
               <p>IN a Cittie was as ancient Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght which wedded a young Wife and a faire as yee haue done, whome hee loued aboue all earthly things. This Knight was a very circūspect and carefull Husband, insomuch that euery night he locked in the dore with his owne handes, and layd the keyes vnder his beds hed. And in this Citie there was a law or custome, that at a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertain houre in the night a Bell was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sed to be rung, &amp; after the ringing of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat Bell, if any men or women were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the Watchmen founde in the Strets, all that night they should be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ept fast in Prison, &amp; on the morrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et vpon a Pillory, that all the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight behold and woonder at them.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:18"/> This foresaid knight had little mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or lust to fleshly deeds, for he was old and might not saciate and perfourme the desires and appetites of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant young wife: Wherefore euerie night she (hauing a Paramour, her Husband sleeping) tooke the keyes and went to her Loue, and when she came home againe, all priuily she laid the keyes vnder her husbands head, and thus played she many times. So it happened vppon a night, that the Knight awaked out from his sleepe, and missed his wife, and also the keys vnder his beds head: wherevpon h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arose vp and went vnto the doores <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and found them open, the which he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> closed and bolted fast within, &amp; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> went vp againe into his chamber, &amp; looked out at the window toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the street: and when it was neer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, about the third cocks crow, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wife came home frō her best beloued and found the doore shut and bolte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:18"/> within, wheeeat she was sorrowfull, neuertheles she knocked to haue come in. Then spake the Knight out of the window, O thou most euill and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane wife, now I know and am full assured, that many a time thou hast forsaken my bed and gone and done adulterie, now thou shalt stand vntill the bell be rung, and that the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may take thee, and do with thee according to the law. The wife an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, my Lord, wherefore lay yee that to me, for in very troth the cause of my being abroad was for no euill, but I was called for by my Mothers maide, &amp; fetched in the night by her, and when I saw you sleepe so sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I durst not awake you because yee are old, and therefore I tooke the keyes and went to my mother who is so sore sicke, that I feare to morrow shee must be annointed or anneyled: notwithstanding, for that I would not offend you, I haue hasted againe
<pb facs="tcp:178576:19"/> to you, and haue left her lying in great paine and infirmitie, therefore I pray you for the loue of GOD let mee in before the Bell ringeth. The Knight answered, ye shall not so come in, yee must there abide vnto the time that the Bell ringeth, and vntill that the Watchmen come and take you: then sayd she, that shold be to you &amp; to me and to all our friends &amp; kindred a great shame and reproch, therfore for the reuerence of almighty God let me come in: then sayd he, haue in thy mine (euill and false wife) how often times thou hast forsaken my bed and done adulterie, it is much better that thou suffer shame, and bewayle thy sinnes here in this world, than for to suffer paine in Hell: shee sayd agayne to him, I pray you for the loue of him that was crucified, and died on the crosse, haue pittie on me: the Knight answered, thou labourest in vaine, for thou shalt not come in, but shalt tarry
<pb facs="tcp:178576:19"/> the comming of the Watchmen. She hearing that, sayd: My Lord, you knowe well that by this dore stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a Well, if ye let me not come in, I shall therein drowne my selfe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than all me frends should be sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for me: then said he, would God that thou haddest beene drowned long before euer thou camest in my bed. As they thus spake together, the Moone went down, &amp; all was dark: then sayd she, if it will none otherwise be, I shall drowne my selfe, but yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, like a true Christian woman, I will make my Testament. First I bequeath to GOD my soule, and my bodie to be buried in the Church of Saint Peter: and of all other things and goods that GOD hath sent me, I giue vnto you to dispose for my Soule, after your wisedome and discretion. And when shee had thus sayd, she went to the Well and there lying a great stone, with both
<pb facs="tcp:178576:20"/> her armes, she lift it vp and said, now I drowne my selfe, and cast the stone downe into the well, and went again priuily and stood by the doore: the knight hearing the noyse, cryed with a loud voice, saying: Alas, alas, my wife is drowned, and hastily came downe &amp; ran to the well, and when she saw that the dore was open, anon she entred in and locked the gate, and went vp to the chamber, and lay and looked out of the window: the knight stood by the well and cried and wept bitterly, and said, woe be to mee, I haue nowe lost my most best beloued wife, cursed be the time that I made fast the dore against her. The Lady heard that and said, O thou cursed ould Greysard, why standest thou there this time of the night, was not my bodie to thee sufficient? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe yee thus euery night out to your Harlots and your whoores, and leaue my bed? As he heard the voice
<pb facs="tcp:178576:20"/> of his Wife, hee was right glad, and sayd, blessed be God that yet shee is not drowned: but my good Ladye, wherefore lay you such things against me? I thought to haue chasticed you, and therefore I locked the dore, but in no wise I intended your perill: yee know well wat sorrow I made for you when I heard you to haue fallen into the Wel, &amp; therfore I came light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue holpen you. Whereupon she said, thou lyest falsly, I neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted such default as thou layest to mee, but it appeareth by a common Prouerbe, he that is guilty or culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himselfe in a sin, hee iudgeth euery man to be in the same, or else, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neuer sought his sonne in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, except hee had been therein him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe: so in like case conceiuest thou a false surmise of me, but one thing I promise thee, thou shalt abide there vntill the Watchmen come, and the Bell hee runge, that they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:21"/> thee before the Iudges to abide and suffer the law. Then said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Knight, wherefore lay you such things to mee that am old, impotent, and most vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet to delight in such game? I haue been conuersant in this Citie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was defamed, and therefore let me in, that to me &amp; to your selfe ye doe no shame. She said, ye speak in vaine, it is better that ye forethinke your sinnes rather in this World, than in Hell, haue in mind what y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wise man sayth, a poore man proud, a rich man a liar, an old man a foole, God hateth: so be yee a foole and rich, what neede was it to you for to slaunder me, and cannot be content when as yee haue the flower of my youth at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, but yet runnest to Harlots? it is the great grace of God, that you, haue tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; space to forethinke you, least ye should perish and be damned for more sins, &amp; therefore suffer your pennance now patiently. The knight
<pb facs="tcp:178576:21"/> sayd, O my best beloued Ladie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be so, yet is God mercifull, and he asketh nothing of a sinner, but that he amend his life, and forethinke himselfe, and do penance for his sins. Now let me come in &amp; I will make amends: she sayd, what Deuill hath made you so good a Preacher, but so come you not in: and as they thus spake the bell rang, then he intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted feruently, saying, now suffer me to come in that I be not ashamed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: she answered, the ringing of the Bell pretendeth the health of your soule. And as this was said, came the Watchmen about y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> City, and found the Knight standing in the street, and sayd vnto him, O good man it is not good that ye stand here in this houre of the night. As she heard the voice of the Watchmen, shee sayd: good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes venge me on that old accursed Whoremonger, for ye knowe whose Daughter I am this curssed old man
<pb facs="tcp:178576:22"/> is wont euery night to leaue my bed, and go to his whores and harlots, I haue long forborne him, and would not shew it, ne complaine vppon him to my friends, for I trusted that hee would haue amended his misrule, &amp; it helpeth not, and therefore take him and punish him according to the law, that all such old Dotards may take example by him. Then the watchmē tooke him, and all night chasticed him in prison, and on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morrow they set him on the Pillorie. Now said the Maister to the Emperor, Lord, haue ye vnderstood what I haue said? and he said, right well. Thē said the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, if you put your son to death by the instigatiō of your wife, it shall chance to you worse than to the Knight.</p>
               <p>The Emperour said, she was the worst woman that euer I heard off, that so falsely brought her husband to shame and rebuke: I say vnto you Maister, that for the reason of this
<pb facs="tcp:178576:22"/> example my sonne shall not die this day. The master said vnto him, if you doe so, then doe you wisely, and that hereafter you shall ioy: and so I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to God, &amp; thanke you of your patient hearing, and for the sparing of your Sonne, and so departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>WHen the Empresse heard that the Child was not yet dead, she wept bitterly, and entred into her priuie Chamber, and tare her skinne with her nayles, &amp; with a loud voide cryed, alas that euer I was borne, that I so great a Kinges daughter should thus be reproched &amp; shamed, and thereof can haue no remedie: her Gentlewomen hearing this went &amp; shewed it to the Emperor, &amp; he went vnto her and comforted her, saying, O Lady, weepe not so, for it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth you not. And she answered, the loue that I haue and owe vnto you,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:23"/> maketh me more to sorrow, than the contempt of the death, for why the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward loue of your hart hath hitherto prohibited and letted me that I haue not retourned againe into my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to my Father, but I feare if I should so doe, it might turne you to harme, for hee is mightie to honour mee with riches, and to reuenge my quarrell &amp; despight in such wise that you might repent it. Whereto said the Emperour, let that passe out of your minde, neither repeat it any more, for as long as I liue, I shall neuer fayle you. And she sayd, Lord I pray God that ye may long liue, but I feare me that it shall happen to you as it fell to a Knight &amp; his Sonne that would not burie his Fathers head in the Churchyard, and yet his Father was for him slaine: then said the Emperor shew me y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> example how it was that he would not bury his Fathers head: she sayd, I shall doe it to your profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:23"/>
               <head>The third Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>IN the Cittie of Roome there was a Knight which had two Daughters and one Son. This Knight had so great delight in hunting, Iusting &amp; tourney, and all thing that he might win &amp; get, he laid it and spent it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. In that time liued the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour named <hi>Octauian,</hi> which in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of gold and siluer exceeded al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kinges and Princes, insomuch that he had a Tower full of Gold, &amp; ordained a Knight to haue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> keping &amp; charge therof. This Knight that so haunted Iusting &amp; other idle games, came to so great pouerty, that he was disposed to sell his heritage, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to him his sone, and said, my Son it behooueth me of your counsell, for necessitie and pouertie compelleth me to sell mine heritage, or else to finde another way by which I may liue, for if I should sell mine heritage, ye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178576:24"/> your Sisters should perish. The son said, Father if we can find any maner of meane without selling of our heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, I should be readie to helpe you. The Father said, I haue bethought me of good councell: The Emperour hath a Tower full of gould, let vs go by night time thither with instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and digge and hew through the tower, and let vs take of the gold as much as shall suffice vs. Whereto answered the son and said, that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saile cannot be amended, for it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to take of the Emperours gold to helpe vs, than to sell our inheritance. So they arose vp both on a night, &amp; went to the tower, and with instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they made a hole through the wall, and tooke as much gould as they both could carrie away at that time, and the knight paid his debts and haunted againe Iusts as he did before, vntill that all was spent and consumed. In the meane while, the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:24"/> keeper of the Treasure went into the Tower, and when he saw the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure stollen, and a great hole made through the wall, he began to waxe sore affraid, &amp; went to the Emperour and shewed him what was befallen: to whome the Emperor said all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly, what needest thou to tell me that? haue I not deliuered to thee my Treasure, and therefore of thee will I aske it againe? As y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> keeper heard that, he went to the Tower againe, and set afore the hole a great vessell full of pitch mingled with other gins so subtilly, that no man might come in an that hole, but that he must needs fall into that vessell, and then falling thereinto, he could no more get out of it. Not long after, the Knight had consumed and spent all the gold, and went againe with his son to the tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to steale more. And as the Father went in first, anon he was fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Vessell with pitch vp to the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:25"/> necke, and when he saw that he was taken and could not get out, hee sayd to his Son, follow me not, for if thou doest, thou canst not escape by any meanes: then said the son, God forbid that I should not help you, for if you are found, we are a but dead, &amp; if that ye may not be hopen by me, I shall seeke counsaile how that you may bee deliuered &amp; holpen. The Father said, there is none other counsaile but with thy sword smite off my head, and as my bodie is found without an head, no man shall knowe me, and so thou and my Daughters may scape and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide this worldly shame and death. The sonne said, father ye haue giuen the best councell, for if it were so, that any man might perceiue any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of you, none of vs should escape that death: and therefore it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient that your head bee smitten off: anon he drewe out his Sword and smote off his Fathers head and cast
<pb facs="tcp:178576:25"/> it into a pit, and then went and shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto his Sisters all the matter, who many dayes after priuily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled the death of their father. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, the keeper of the Treasure came into the Tower, &amp; found there a bodie without any head, whereat he wondred sore, and shewed it to the Emperour, to whome he sayd, binde that body to the taile of an horse, and so draw it through all the streets of the Cittie, and diligently take good heed if ye heate any cry or weeping: wheresoeuer ye heare that he is Lord of the house, take all them, and with the body draw them to the gallowes and hang them. The which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours seruants fulfilled according to his commandement, and as they came right against the house of the dead Knight, the daughters seeing the bodie of their dead Father, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently made a maruaylous great shrike &amp; went pitiously, and as their
<pb facs="tcp:178576:26"/> brother head that, anon he wounded himselfe in the mouth with a knife, so that great plentie of bloud came out of the wound: the officers when they heard the crie, entred into the house, demaunding the cause of their cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: then answered the Son, they lament because I am thus wounded, for when my sisters saw my blood so aboundantly goe out, as yee see, they began to weepe &amp; crye and when the officers saw the wound, then belieued his words, &amp; so deceiued, went their waies and hung the Knights bodie vpon the gallowes, where he hung a long time, and his son would neither take his bodie downe from the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, nor yet burie his head. The Empresse said, vnderstand ye what I haue said? the emperor said, very wel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Declaration of the Example.</head>
               <p>THen spake the Empresse thus, my Lord, I feare it will so chance to
<pb facs="tcp:178576:26"/> you to your son. This Knight for the loue of his son was made poore, and first he committed theft, &amp; brake the Tower, secondarily caused him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to be headed, that his Children should haue no shame, after that his son cast his head into a dike, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it neither in church nor in church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, but suffered his bodie to hange still vppon the gallowes: if that hee could not haue taken it downe in the day, he might well haue done it in the night. In the same manner ye labour night and day, tat ye may promote your son to honour &amp; riches, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt he dayly laboureth for your confusion and destruction, that hee may raign after you in your Empire. Therfore I aduise you that you cause him to be hanged before hee destroye you: the Emperour sayde, you haue shewed mee a good example. The Knights Sonne when he had smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off his Fathers head, would not
<pb facs="tcp:178576:27"/> burie it: without doubt my Sonne shall not doe so by me, but he anon commaunded his Officers that they should lead him to the Gallowes, and they all obayed his commaundement hastily, and as they led him through the Streets, the people made great noyse and lamentations, crying alas, alas, the onely Son of the Emperor is led againe toward the Gallowes: and as they led him, the third Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster named <hi>Craton,</hi> came ryding by, and as the Child saw him bowed downe his head to him, as though he had sayd, haue minde vpon me, and the people cryed, O good Maister, hast you, and saue your Disciple, and so hee rode with great speed to the Emperour. And when be came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, he most humbly saluted him: and said, thy coming hither shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer auaile thee, for I thinke it long to be reuenged of thee. The Maister said, I hoped at my coming to haue
<pb facs="tcp:178576:27"/> been welcome, and haue had a better reward, and not to bee so rebuked. The Emperour said, as yee haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued so shall it be to you. To whom he said, My Lord, what haue I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued? the Emperour sayd, ye right well deserue death, for I deliuered to you my son well speaking, and well mannered, for to be enfourmed and taught, and ye haue deliuered him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to me dumbe &amp; a Ribaud. To whom y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Master said, in that you say he is dum, that I commit to god, for he maketh the dumme to speake, and the deaf to heare: but in that you say hee would haue enforced your wife, that would I gladly knowe, if any creature haue seene that, for there is no malice aboue the malice of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; that shall I prooue by a good example, that a woman is full of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings and deceptions, and if you put to death your Sonne for the wordes of your wife, it shall happen to you
<pb facs="tcp:178576:28"/> as it did to a rich Burgesse of his wife and his Pie, the which he loued maruailously. To whom the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour said, I pray you tell mee how that women are full of malice and leasings: who said, I will not shew it, but if you will first call againe your son from the death, then at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure I shall shew the example. Then the Emperour anon made his sonne to be called againe, and to be put in pryson. And the Maister beganne to tell the Example in this fourme fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the third Maister.</head>
               <p>THere was in a Citie a rich Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesse that had a Pie, the which hee loued so much, that euery day hee taught her to speake Latine and Hebrue: and when she had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned very perfitly to speake these two Languages, all that she saw &amp; heard shee shewed and told to her Maister.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:28"/> This young man man had a faire young n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fe as ye haue, the which he loued much, but shee on the contrarye loued not him, because he might not furnish her of such pleasures and lusts as she desired to haue, and therefore had shee another faire young man that shee loued aboue her Husband, and alwaies as her Husband was out of the towne about his Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise and other businesse, shee sent for her best beloued, that they might make good there together. The Pie as shee espied that, told it vnto her Maister at his comming home, in such wise, that the noyse ranne all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Cittie of her adulterie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Husband many times brab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and chidde with her: she answered him, ye beleeue your cursed Pie which as long as shee liueth, shall alwayes make betwixt vs variance and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: and hee sayde, the Pie cannot lye, for what shee seeth and heareth,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:29"/> that she telleth me, and therefore I belieue her more than you. It tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that this man went into farre Countries about his Marchandize, and assoone as he was gone, his wife sent for her friend and Loue to solace and make good cheere with him, but he durst not come by day light, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode till the euening, least he should be seen and marked of the people: and when night was come, he knocked at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gate, and shee was ready &amp; opened it, and said, goe in freely, for no man shal see you, &amp; he said, I feare me that the cursed Pie shall accuse vs, for by her is come great slaunder vppon vs throughout all the Citie. Enter in she said boldly and feare not, and as they should passe through the Hall where the Pie was in her Cage, shee heard say these words, O my best beloued, I feare me greatly, least that the Pie shall bewray vs. And as the wife heard that, she said, be still foole, it is
<pb facs="tcp:178576:29"/> darke she may not see you. Then the Pie hearing that sayd, if I see thee not, yet I heare thy voice, and thou doest wrong to my Maister, for thou sleepest with my Mistresse, and when my Master commeth I shal tell him. The young man hearing that, sayd, told I not you that the Pie shoulde discouer vs. And the wife sayd, feare not, for this night wee shall be auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on the Pie, and so they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the chamber, &amp; slept together that night. About midnight y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wife arose and called her Mayd and said, fetch me a Ladder and set it vp to the roofe of the house that I may wreake mee vppon the Pie: the Mayd did euen so, and they both went vp and made an hole through the couering of the house, right ouer against the Pie, and there-through cast sand, clay, stones, and water vppon the Pie, in so much that the poore Pie was neere dead. And on the morrow the young man
<pb facs="tcp:178576:30"/> went early out at the backe dore: and when the good man was comming home, as his custome was, hee went and visited his Pie, and sayd to her, O Pie my beloued Bird, tell me how thou hast fared all the whiles that I haue been out? She said, Maister I shall tell you tydings that I haue heard: your wife assoone as you were gone, by the night time shee let a man come in, and assoone as I heard that, I told him that I would shew it you at your comming home, yet notwithstanding she led him into your Chamber, and slept with him al night: you asked mee also how that I haue done in your absence, and I say to you of a troth, that I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so neere my death as I was that same night with snow, haile, &amp; raine, that fell vpon me, so long together, that I was almost left for dead. The wife when shee heard that, said to her husband, Sir you beleeue your
<pb facs="tcp:178576:30"/> Pie, now may ye heare what she saith shee complaineth that in the same night, there fell so much snowe, haue; and raine vpon her, that shee was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most dead, and yet there was none of them all that same night, for there was not in a yeere a fairer, nor a clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer night that it was, &amp; therfore from henceforth belieue her not: then went the good man to his neighbours, and asked of them, if in that night there were any hayle or raine, they answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that some of them had waked all that night, and in all that yeere they had not seen a fairer night: thē went he to his house and said to his wife, I haue found you in the troth, for the night was faire and cleare, as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand of your neighbors. You may now know of a troth, said shee, that the Pie is a Lyar, and with her lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings she hath sowne &amp; made discord betwixt vs, and moreouer I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed through the Cittie by her false
<pb facs="tcp:178576:31"/> leasings. Then the Burgesse went to the Pie, and said, wherefore hast thou made lyes and false tales be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt mee and my wife, is this the thanke that I haue for the meat that I was wont to giue thee with mine owne hands euery day, and thou hast also thereby brought my wife into great defamation through all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? The Pie answered, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth I cannot lye, for that I saw and heard, haue I shewed you, then said he, thou lyest, hast thou not said that in that same night was Haile and Snowe, and rayne, that thou hadst neere hand lost thy life, which is false? and therefore from hencefoorth thou shalt make no more leasings nor dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betwixt me and my wife, and so tooke the Pie and brake her necke. As the wife sawe that, she was glad, and said, now haue ye done well, now may we all our life dayes liue in rest and peace. And when he had killed
<pb facs="tcp:178576:31"/> the Pie, he looked vp and saw in the top of the house a Ladder, and a ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell with water, sand, and stones, and as he beheld that, he perceiued the falshood of his wife, and cried with a loude voice, woe be vnto me, that for my wiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wordes I haue killed my Pie, and also my solace &amp; ioy lost, the which in all things said to me troth. And as he had thus done, anon for sorrow he left his Marchandise, and all his house, and went towards the Holy land, and neuer turned agayne towards his wife. Then the Master said to the Emperour, Sir, haue you vnderstood what I haue said? hee answered right well, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Maister said, was not that a false and cursed wife, that so by her leasings caused the Pie to be killed? The Emperour said, in troth she was full of falsenesse, it piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me greatly to thinke vppon the Pie, the which for her true saying, lost her life. Verily I must say vnto
<pb facs="tcp:178576:32"/> you, that you haue told me a faire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, therefore this day my Son shall not die. Then said the Maister, Sir you doe wisely, and I thanke you that you haue spared your sonne this day for my sake, and so to god I commend you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Fourt Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>WHen the Empresse heard that the child was not yet dead, she made great noyse and crying, in such wise that shee was heard through the Palaice, and said, woe be vnto me that euer I was made Empresse, would to God I had dyed when I was first brought into these parts: when the Emperour heard the noyse and crie that she made, he presently entred into her Chamber and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted her as much as he might, and demaunded the cause of her lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who said: O my most louing Lord, haue you no woonder, though
<pb facs="tcp:178576:32"/> that I be in this sorrow and agonie, for I am your wife, and in your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie by your Sonne I am shamed, and yee saw me lately all be bled and scratched, and you haue promised mee that he therefore should be hanged, and yet he liueth, wherefore should I not be sorrie? the Emperor answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, be content &amp; pleased, and I shall do Iustice vpon my Son to morrow, but in that I forbare him yesterday, was at the motion of one of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, by an example: then said shee, haue yee forbid to doe Iustice for one word? were it so for all the world, ye should not let to doe Iustice, and yee say for the example of one Maister you haue stayed it. I feare me it shall happen to you &amp; with your Masters, as vpon a time it fortuned to an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror with his seuen wise Maisters. The Emperour said, I pray you tell me that same example. Shee said, to what intent should I so labour all in
<pb facs="tcp:178576:33"/> vayne? for yesterday I shewed you a good example, and it auayled not, and whatsoeuer I shew you for your honour and profit, that the Maisters of your Sonne turne vp and downe to your destruction, as is this present example I shall clerely shew you: to whome the Emperour said, O my best beloued Lady, tell me that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that therby I may the better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware hereafter, for though that I respite my sonnes life for one day, I shall not therefore giue him his life, for that which is deferred is not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forgiuen: and she said, gladly I shall shew it you for your profit, and beganne to tell it, as hereafter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Fourth Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>SOmetime there was in the Citie of Rome seuen wise Maisters, by whome all the Empire was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned and ruled, and the Emperour
<pb facs="tcp:178576:33"/> that then was, did neuer attempt any thing without the councell of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters: wherevppon, they perceiuing that the Emperour was so affected and enclyned to them, that without them he would not ordained or doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, diuised by their Arte and cunning, that the Emperour should cleerely see as long as hee was in the Pallace, but as soone as hee was out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Pallace, he should become blind: and that did they, to the intent that they might the more freely haue the dealing themselues of all things that appertained to the Emperour, by the which they gotte and wanne to them great profit and lucre of goods: and after they had made and wrought the experiment, they could neuer change it, ne vndo it afterward, but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour abode still blind many yeares. And the seauen Maisters made and proclaymed throughout the Empire, that if any mā had dreamed a dream
<pb facs="tcp:178576:34"/> hee should come vnto them with a floren of gold or Siluer, &amp; they would expound and declare vnto him the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of his dreame: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and by other vniust meanes, they obtained much more substance and Money of the people, than the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour did. So vpon a time when he sat at the table with the Empresse, he began to sigh and sorrow in himselfe, and when she perceiued that, she en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired diligently of him the cause of his heauinesse &amp; dolour: the Emperor said, should it not be heauie and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull to mee, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I so long haue been blind, &amp; cannot see out of my Pallace, and yet can haue or find no remedy? To whom spake the Empresse &amp; said Lord heare my counsaile, and it shall neuer repent you if you do thereafter. In your Court you haue seauen wise Maisters, by whome yee and all the Empire is gouerned, if you now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and marke this in your minde,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:34"/> yee shall finde, that they are the cause of your blindnesse and disease, and if it be so, they are worthy to dye a most shamefull death, therefore take heede to my councell and aduise: first send for them, &amp; shew to them your disease and infirmitie, and threaten them on paine of their liues, that they should find some speedy remedy to helpe you of your sicknes and blindnesse. This councell pleased the Emperour well, and anon hee sent for the Maisters, &amp; when they were come, the Emperor anon shewed to them his infirmitie, and blindnesse, and charged them on paine of death, that they should pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently seeke some remedy to ease him thereof. Then answered they, ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of vs a thing that is difficult and hard to be done thus shortly, but giue vs respite for ten dayes, and then we shall giue you our full answere. The Emperour was therewith well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and pleased: then the seuen wise
<pb facs="tcp:178576:35"/> Maysters went to councell how they might restore vnto him his sight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and in no manner of wise could they finde the meane how to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the blindnes from the Emperor, wherfore they were all right sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and sayde among themselues, without wee finde a remedye, wee are all but dead men. So they went from thence throughout all the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and sought if they could finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny remedy or councell therefore. It happened them vppon a time, going through a Cittie, and in the middest thereof, they found Children playing and after them came a man with a talent or floren of Gould, and sayd to them, good Maisters, this night I haue dreamed a dreame, the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof I would faine knowe, wherefore I pray you shew me what it signifieth, &amp; take this gold to you. That heard one of the Children that played among the other, and sayd to
<pb facs="tcp:178576:35"/> him: giue mee the Gould and then I shall expound thy dreame. The man sayd, I dreamed this night that in the middest of my Orchard, was a great spring of Water, whereof came many small springs, that all mine Orcharde was full and ouerflowne with water: the Child sayd, take a Spade and digge in the same place whereas ye thought that the water spronge out, and there shall yee finde and Hoord of Gould so great, that yee and all your Children and Lyneage shall be for euer rich: the man did as the Childe had shewed him, and found the Treasure according to his woordes. Then went the man to the Child and offered him a pounde waight of the Gould that hee hadde founde, for the interpretation of his dreame, but hee would receiue none, but committed him to the prayers of the man. The seuen Maisters, when they heard the Childe so wisely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
<pb facs="tcp:178576:36"/> the dreame, they sayd to him, good Child what is your name? He answered and said, I am called <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line.</hi> Then said the Maisters, wee see surely great wisedome in you, we shall shew vnto you a strange matter, and of that wee would gladly that ye could finde a remedy. The Child said, shew vnto me your matter: and they sayd, the Emperour of Rome as long as he is in his Pallace hath his sight very cleere without any impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment, and as soone as hee is gone of his Pallace, he is so blind that he cannot see. Now if yee can finde out the cause thereof, and giue present remedy whereby he may be eased and haue his sight againe, ye shall haue great reward and honour of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror: then answered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> child, I know aswell the cause of his blindnesse, as the remedy. They said all vnto him, come with vs to the Emperour, and yee shall be rewarded so largely, that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:36"/> yee shall be pleased. To whome the Childe sayd, I am ready to goe with you. And when they came with the Childe before the Emperour, they said to him: Lord, lo here is the child that we haue brought before you, the which shall fulfill your desires tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the cause of your blindnes, and to recouering of your sight: the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayde, Good Maisters will you take vppon you, and abide there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that the Childe shall perfourme this attempt? They all sayd yea, for we be expert in his wisedome. The Emperour turned himselfe towards the Child and said, will ye vndertake to tell me the cause of my blindnesse, and the remedy? the child answered and sayd, My Lord the Emperour, leade mee into your bedde Chamber, and there I shall shew you what is to bee doone, and as hee was therein brought, hee said to he Seruants, take of the Clothes of the bed, and all
<pb facs="tcp:178576:37"/> the apparell, &amp; ye shall see woonders. And as that was done they sawe a Well smoking that had seuen springs or Flouds, the which when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sawe, hee maruailed greatly. The Child sayd, ye see this Well, and without it be quenched, yee shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue your sight, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperour said how may that bee? the Childe sayde, but by one way: the Emperour sayd, shewe vs then the meane, and if it bee possible to mee, it shall be done, that I may recouer againe my sight, as well without, as within. To whome the Child sayd, My Lord, the vii. springs of this Well, are these Seauen wise Maisters, who hitherto haue tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terously gouerned you and your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and haue made you blind as ye bee without yur Pallace, that they your subiects by extortion might pill and poule, ye not seeing it. But now they know not the remedy, therefore here you now my counsaile, and this
<pb facs="tcp:178576:37"/> Well shall bee quenched and extinct: strike of the first Maisters head, and anon hee shall the first spring quench, and so by order one after another, till that they are all beheaded, and anon all the springs with the Well shall be vanished and gone away, and ye shall haue againe your sight as ye had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and when this was done &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, the well with the seuen springs were vanished, And as the Emperor had his sight againe, hee made the Child a great Lord, and gaue him great abundance of goods: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter spake the Empres, my Lord haue ye well perceiued this Example that I haue told you? and he sayd, yea in the best wise, ye haue recited a worthy and good Example. Then said shee in thy same manner your seuen wise Maisters intend to doe with you, with their false narrations, that your Sonne may raigne ouer your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which God forbid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:38"/>
               <head>The declaration of the Example.</head>
               <p>THis Well is your Sonne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out floweth vii. springs that sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifyeth the Seuen wise Maisters, the which Son ye may not destroye, without the seuen wise Maisters bee made feeble and brought to naught: that done, this Well that is your son, with all his whiles shall not escape, but let him be hanged first, least hee haue helpe of his Maisters, and after consequently the seuen Maisters, and so you shall gouerne and guide your Empire in rest and peace. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour anon commaunded his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to lead his Sonne to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, which they were loath to doe. And there was then so great a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people gathered with great noyse and bewayling, that the noyse came to the eares of the Fourth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster named <hi>Malquidrake,</hi> the which leapt vppon his horse, and hasted him
<pb facs="tcp:178576:38"/> to the Pallace. Where he met with his Disciple and did reuerence to him and commended him vnto him: and when hee came before the Emperour, and had done his obeisance and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence as appertained, the Emperor then answered &amp; sayd; Little thanks shall you haue ye ould cursed Caytysse for so ill teaching of my Sonne. I deliuered you my Sonne well spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, &amp; in all things right vertuous, but you haue sent him home a foole, dumbe, and a ribaud, for hee would haue laine with my wife by force, and therefore all yee with him together shall be hanged. Then said the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, my Lord, I haue not deserued so ill of you. God knoweth why your son speaketh not, in short time you shall perceiue other things, but the time is not yet come, but in that you say he would haue oppressed your wife, that is not true, nor prooued, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for one single person should you
<pb facs="tcp:178576:39"/> iudge your Sonne to death. If now for the words of your wife, yee iudge your Sonne to dye, it will be worse to you, than to a certaine old man and his wife, and that I shall well proue. To whome the Emperor said, think you to doe with mee yee old Doters, as sometime seuen wise men did to an Emperour. Whereunto sayde the Maisters, the offence and trespasse of one, or yet of Twenty, may not sound to the rebuke and blame of all other, for ouer all the World there bee both good and euill, but one thing of a troth I shall shewe to you, that euill shall come to you if you this day put your Sonne to death for the wordes of your Wife, the which I could shew by a notable example. Then said the Emperour, will yee recite that for our learning: the Maister said, if ye will call again your Sonne, and keep him till I haue made declaration of the Example, (&amp; afterwards as ye shall
<pb facs="tcp:178576:39"/> thinke good to doe with him, doe it) then will I rehearse the example, or else not. The Emperour commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that hee should bee called againe, and he desired the Maister to say, as here after followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the Fourth Maister.</head>
               <p>THere was an old Knight (and a right wise man) that liued long without wife or Child.</p>
               <p>His friends came to him many times and coūsailed and exhorted him, that he should take a wife.</p>
               <p>The Knight thus counsailed, and stirred by his Friends so often times, at the last hee agreed to them, and they gaue him to Wife the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Prouost of Roome, that was rich and right faire, whome when hee had seene, anon hee was made blind and taken in her loue, and began to loue her maruailously well: and whē they had been married a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:178576:40"/> space together, &amp; had no Child. Vppon a time in a morning it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that shee went to the Church, where shee met with her Mother, whome she saluted as it behoued. My deere Daughter sayde the Mother, how pleaseth you your mariage, and your Husband? shee said, right euill, for yee haue giuen to me an old lame man to my discontentment in all res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, and I would you had the same time buried mee, for I had rather lye and eate with a swine, than with him, and therefore I may no longer thus endure, but I must needes loue another: then said the Mother, God forbid that my deare Daughter, how long time haue I been with your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; yet neuer hitherto haue I med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with such foolishnes; the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sayd, Mother it is no maruaile, for you both met in your youth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; the one took solace of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other, but I can receiue of him no manner
<pb facs="tcp:178576:40"/> of corporall pleasure, for he is cold &amp; on the bed he lyeth as still as a stone, or as a thing immoueable. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther answered, if you will loue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, tell me what he is? the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter sayd, I will loue a Priest. To whome the mother sayd, it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; lesse sin for you to loue a Knight or a squier, than a Priest: nay, quoth the Daughter, if I should loue a Knight or a Squier, in short time he would be wearie of me, and after that hee would doe me shame, and so will not the Priest, for hee will hold and keepe his owne honour &amp; counsell, as well as mine, also spirituall men be more true to their loues, that secular men be: the Mother said, heare my counsell, and it will bee good for you. Old folke are wyllie &amp; fell, tempt your husband first, &amp; if ye escape him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing you harme or smiting, then loue the Priest. The Daughter said, I may not so long abide. The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:178576:41"/> sayd, vpon my blessing abide till yee haue prooued him: the Daughter sayd, vppon your blessing I will abide so long till I haue attempted him, but first tell mee how that I shall prooue him? the Mother sayd, he hath in his Orchard a tree which he loueth much, cause it to be smitten downe while hee is out at hunting, and against his comming home make him a fire therewith, and if he forgiue it you, then may you surely loue the Priest. As shee heard that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of her Mother, shee heard that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of her Mother, shee went home, to whome her Husband sayd, where haue you beene so long? shee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, I haue been at the Church, where I met with my Mother, and with her I haue a little talked and commumed, and so beganne properly for to dissemble: after Mid-day the Knight rode out for to hunt, then shee thinking vppon the counsaile of her Mother, went to the Gardiner,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:41"/> and sayd to him, cut downe this yong Tree newly Planted, that I may make a fier thereof to warme my Lord withall at his comming home from hunting, for it is a great wind and right sharpe cold: the Gardiner sayd, Madame that will I not doe, for my Lord loueth this Tree better than he doth all the other Trees, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthelesse I shall well helpe you to gather wood ynough for to make a good fier, but in any wise this I will not hewe downe. As she heard that, then bouldly shee tooke the Axe from the Gardener, and hewed downe the Tree herselfe, and made the Garde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner with other to beare it home. At e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening when her Lord came from hunting, he was very cold: and shee made a great fier, and went and met with him, and set him a stoole before the fier to warme him: and as hee a little while had sitten, he perceiued y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> odour of the fier, and called to him
<pb facs="tcp:178576:42"/> the Gardener and said, I feele by this odour, that the newe Plant burneth in the fire. The Gardiner said, Lord it is true, my Ladye your wife hath felled it downe: the Knight sayd to her, God forbid that my Plant should be cut downe by you; shee answered anon and sayd, Lord I haue done it, knowing the weather cold, &amp; you also cold, and therefore I haue ordained this fier for your comfort. As the Knight heard that, he looked angerly vpon her, and sayd, O cursed woman, how wast thou so hardy as to hewe downe so gentle a young Tree, the which thou knowest well that I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aboue all my other Trees? When he had so said, she began to weep and excuse her selfe and said, my Lord, I haue done it for your good, and doe you take it so greeuously, and began to crie woe, woe be to me? anon as the Knight sawe the weeping &amp; teares of his wife, and heard her cause, he was
<pb facs="tcp:178576:42"/> mooued with pittie, and said to her, cease of your weeping, and beware how that yee anger mee any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or trouble mee in any thing that I loue. The next day early in the morning, she went againe to the church yar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, &amp; met with her mother comming home, and they saluted each other. Then the Daughter said to the Mother ah deere Mother I will loue the Priest, for I haue attempted my Lord, as ye counsailed me, but all for nought, for hee anon forgaue it when he sawe me a little weep. Then said the Mother, though old men one time forgiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they double the paine another time and therfore I counsaile you that you yet once againe attempt him.</p>
               <p>Then said the Daughter, I may not any longer abide, for I suffer much paine for the loue of the Priest, that with my tongue I cannot tel it, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee shall pardon mee, I will no more follow or doe after yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell:
<pb facs="tcp:178576:43"/> then said the mother, for the loue that the Child should haue vnto the mother, attēpt him yet once more for your Fathers blessing, and then if yee goe quite without any harme or bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, loue the Priest in the name of God. Then answered the Daughter it is to mee great pain so long time to abide, neuertheles for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> blessing of my Father I shal once more attempt him, but tell me how I shall beginne? the Mother sayd, I vnderstand that he hath a little hound that hee loueth well &amp; keepeth his bed, cast the hound with so great might before his face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the wall, that it die, and if yee scape without a stripe, or that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue you it lightly, then in the name of God, loue the Priest. Then sayd the Daughter, I shall in all things doe after your counsaile, for there is no Daughter liuing at this day, that would more gladly haue the blessing of the Father and Mother, that I.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:43"/> And so she bad her Mother farewell, and went to her house againe, &amp; that day with great importunitie &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of heart, shee brought to the night. And when the night was come, shee commaunded the bedde to be couered with purple and cloth of Gould, whiles the Knight sate by the fier: &amp; when the bed was thus made ready, the litle hound as he was accustomed leapt vpon the bed, and shee tooke him by the hinder legges, and with a wood and malicious heart she cast it against the wall that it lay still dead: when the good old Knight saw that, he was maruailously angry, and said with a loud voice to his wife, O thou most cruell and spitefull of all wicked women, how couldest thou find in thine heart to kill that little gentle hound that I loued so much? Lord sayd shew, haue ye not seene how the hound with his feete (comming out of the myre) hath berayed our bedde
<pb facs="tcp:178576:44"/> that is so preciously couered with rich cloathes? and the Knight sayd with much anger, knew you not that I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much better my little Hound thou the bed? when she heard that, anon shee beganne pitiously to weepe, and sayd, woe be to mee that euer I was borne, for all things that I doe for the best, it is all turned into the worst. The Knight would not suffer the weeping and lamenting of his wife, but for that he loued her so much he sayd vnto her, cease your weeping, for I forgiue it you altogether, and I counsayle you that yee beware how that ye displease me from henceforth, and so they went to bed together.</p>
               <p>Vppon the morrowe shee arose vp early and went to the Church where she met with her Mother, to whome, when shee had done reuerence as it behoued, shee sayd, Mother now will I loue the Priest, for I haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted my Husband the second time,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:44"/> and all things he hath suffered.</p>
               <p>The mother said, O my deere daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there is no crueltie or falshood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the crueltie of ould folkes, and therefore I counsaile you, that you yet once prooue him, vnto whom the Daughter answered, Mother yee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vaine, for if ye wist what and how much paine that I suffer for the Priests loue, yee should rather helpe me, if ye loued me. The Mother said, heare me daughter this one time, and I shall neuer let you more. Thinke how you haue sucked milke out of my breasts, and the great pain that I suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for you at your birth: by these paines my deare Daughter I desire and charge you, that ye deny me not this good petitiō, &amp; I promise to God no more to let you nor hinder you of your intent, but rather to helpe you thereto: then answered the Daughter it is to me a great paine to abstaine me, and to forbeare my selfe so long
<pb facs="tcp:178576:45"/> from the loue of the Priest, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse for the great charge that ye haue layd to mee, and also for that ye haue made a vow no more for to let mee, but to further me, tell me how I shall attempt him, &amp; I shall yet once more giue the aduenture. The mother said I know well that on Sunday next comming he intendeth to haue vs all to dinner, and there shall be your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and I, and all our friends, with all the best of the City: and when you are set in your place, &amp; all the meats are brought and serued vppon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, fasten on the Keyes priuily that hang at your girdle in the table cloth and then doe you faine to haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten your knife, &amp; say these words, openly: see what a short wit that I am off, I haue forgotten my knife in my chamber, and then rise vp hasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and goe, and the Cloth with all the meates yee shall cast downe and ouerthrow vpon the ground, and if
<pb facs="tcp:178576:45"/> yee escape without paine, I make a vower to God, that I shall neuer let you after. The Daughter sayd, that shall I gladly doe, and so tooke her leaue and departed. The Feast day came, &amp; all as the Mother sayd were bidden, the seruants made ready and couered the table, all were set at the table &amp; the daughter sat ouer against her Lord: and when the table was well serued with meates and other things thereto belonging, the Ladie of the house sayd with a high voyce, see how forgetfull I am, I haue left my knife in my Chamber, which I must fetch, &amp; so rose vp hastily, &amp; drew the cloth with al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meat vpon it with her, and al the gold vessels and salts lay vpon the groūd: the Knight wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed sore angry in hart, but he for shame dissembled before his guests, and cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded another cleane Cloth, and other meats to be brought, and with ioy and mirth hee saluted his guests,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:46"/> to eate &amp; make good cheere, that by him they were all made merrie. The Feast or Dinner done, they gaue all thanks to the Knight, and took their leaues and departed euerie man to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his own howse: vpon the next day in the morning the Knight arose earely and went to the Church, and heard seruice, after which he went to a Barbour, and sayd vnto him, Sir, are you expert in blood-letting in what vaine that I will desire you? he sayd, Sir I am expert in what vaine that yee can name in a mans bodie. The Knight sayd, I am well content come with me, &amp; when he was come to his house, he entred into his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where his Wife lay in bed, &amp; sayd to her rise vp shortly, then sayd shee, what shall I doe vp so early, it is not yet ix. of the clocke? the Knight sayd, you must rise vp, for you must bee letten blood on both your armes: She sayd, I was neuer letten blood,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:46"/> and shall I now bleed? then sayd the Knight that is troth, and therefore yee are a foole: remember ye nor that first ye hewed down my Tree, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time ye killed my little hound, and yesterday ye shamed me afore all our Friendes and Parents, and the fourth is, if I should suffer you thus to goe forth, yee should for euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and shame me: the cause hereof I consider, that ye haue euill &amp; wild blood within your body, and therefore I will that the corrupt blood shall be drawne out, that ye from henceforth shal no more put me to shame and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and so caused to be made a great fier and she stood &amp; cried, &amp; held vp her handes towards Heauen, and sayd, My Lord forgiue this Trespasse, and haue pitie vppon me at this time and I shall neuer more offend you. The Knight said, pray for no mercy, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mercy that God hath wrought towards thee at this present, is this,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:47"/> that except thou holdest out thine arme straight, I shall soone haue thy heart blood, &amp; he said also to the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, smite hard &amp; make a deepe hole in her arme, or else I shall giue you a great stripe: then smote the Barbor so sore that the blood came abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out, &amp; the Knight would not suffer him to staunch it, vntill the time that she chaunged colour in her visage, and as this was done, hee bad it to bee stopped, &amp; willed the Barbor to smite the vaine vppon the other arme, then cryed she with a very loud voyce, My sweet husband, I pray you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion vppon me, for now I die: the Knight answered, wife ye should haue thought vpon this before, are you had done some these three euill torments or despights: then she held out her left arme, and then the Barbour smote therein an hole, that the bloud came out right vgly, and hee suffered her to bleed vnto the time that the colour in
<pb facs="tcp:178576:47"/> her visage changed, &amp; that she swoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: then said the Knight, now bind the arme and stanch it, and said to her now goe to bed and study, and thinke henceforth how you may amend your selfe, or else I shall draw the blood of your heart: and as this was done, he gaue the Barbour his reward, and then he went againe vnto his owne house: and his Wife vnder the hands of her maidens nigh dead, was let to her bed, she bad one of her Maidens goe to her Mother in all hast, and say that I desire her to come speake with mee before I die: the Mother when she had heard that, was glad of the correction of her Daughter, and came hastily to her. When the Daughter hard her Mother; she said, O my most sweete Mother, I am almost dead, for I haue bled so much bloud, that I beleeue I shall not escape the death. Then answered the Mother, sayde I not vnto you, that ould men are
<pb facs="tcp:178576:48"/> right cruell and fell, will ye now loue the Priest? She said, the Diuell may the priest confound and shame, I will neuer one other but my Husband, thē said the Maister to the Emperour, Lord haue ye vnderstood me? and he answered, right well, for amongest all other that euer I haue heard, this was the best example. Three euill deedes she did to her husband, and I doubt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but if shee had done the fourth, shee should haue shamed him for euer. Then said the Master, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I counsaile you that yee beware of your wife, least it happen worse to you, for why, if you put to death your onely Sonne for her words, you shal be deceiued in the end, and for euer ye shall repent it. The Emperour sayd, truely Master this day my Son shal not die. The Maister said, my Lord I thanke you, that ye for mine exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and my sake this day haue spared your Sonne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:48"/>
               <head>The Fift Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>THe Empresse hearing that the Child was not yet dead, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with apparelled her selfe, and caused her Waynes and Carts to be in a readinesse, as though she would haue gone home into her Countrey to her Father, for to haue complayned of the great shame that was done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, and yet could hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o remedie thereof. The Seruants seeing that, went and shewed to the Emperour, that the Empresse was going into her Country: when he perceiued that, hee went to her saying, whither are you going?</p>
               <p>I hoped that you had loued me so much, that in all the world ye would haue sought no solace but with mee. To that she said, that is true, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I goe from you, for I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare of your death, than to see you die, without doubt yee delight so
<pb facs="tcp:178576:49"/> much to heare these Maisters, that it shall happen vnto you as it did vnto <hi>Octauian</hi> the Emperour, the which was so couetous, that the noble men of the Empire buried him quick, and filled his mouth with moulten gold. The Emperour said, deere Wife doe not so, that another time the blame to you or mee might be layd. Then said the Empresse, truely the blame is yours, for haue you not promised me many times that your son should die, and yet he liueth? and therefore from henceforth I wil no more beleue you. Then said the Emperour, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not a King euerie cause lightly to discusse without aduise, &amp; especially vppon his Sonne, vpon whome it is not meete lightly to giue iudgement, and therefore I saye and pray you, that ye will tell me somewhat by the which I may gouerne my selfe: for it is the vtter destruction of a King, with one aduise, and vndiscreetly to
<pb facs="tcp:178576:49"/> giue Iudgement, she answered and said, I wil gladly tell you a notable example, so that from henceforth yee will not bee couetous or desirous to heare the Maisters: and began to say in this fourme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fift Example of the Empresse</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O <hi>Crauianus</hi>
                  </hi> the Emperour raigned in Roome right rich and couetous, and aboue all things he loued gould. The Citizens of Rome that time did much harme, and many great outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to other Nations, insomuch that diuers Nations and Regions were mooued and stirred against the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes. In that time there was Maister <hi>Virgilius</hi> the which excelled in magicke &amp; in other Sciences all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maisters: the Citizens praied him that hee by his Art and cunning would deuise somewhat by the which they of their enemies might haue warning &amp; knowledge before hand.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:50"/>
               <p>Wherby that they might prouide for themselues the better. Hee made by his Art and cunning a tower, and about vppon the tower did cause to bee set as many Images as in all the world were Regions and prouinces, and in the middest of the tower he let to be made and set, an Image which held in his hand an Apple or a great round ball of gould. And euerie I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the tower held in his hand a little bell, and stood turning and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king towards his owne Prouince to him assigned: and as often times as any Prouince would stirre and rebell against the Romaines, so often tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him the Image of the Land, and rang the Bell: That hearing, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of Roome armed themselues, and to that Prouince hastest with all their might, the same to subdue: and so was there no Land so great that could wreake them vppon the Romaynes, and therefore were they
<pb facs="tcp:178576:50"/> dread and feared ouer all the World. Also that Maister <hi>Virgill</hi> made for the solace and comfort of the poore people, and Light that alway burned, &amp; by that light he made two Bathes, the one of them hotte, in the which the poore people might bath &amp; wash themselues: and the other cold, in the which they might themselues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fresh. Betwixt that Light and the Baths, he made an Image standing, in whose forehead was written, hee that smiteth mee, shall anone haue vengeaunce. The Image stoode there many yeares, at the last there came a Clarke &amp; beheld the Image, &amp; read this writing, &amp; thought in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, what vengeaunce hee might finde therefore: I belieue better that if any man should smite thee, and that thou fallest therewith to the earth, hee should finde some treasure vnder thy feete, and therefore is thy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that no man should haue it. And
<pb facs="tcp:178576:51"/> the Clarke lift vp his hand and gaue the Image a great stroake that it fell on the ground, and anon the light was out, and the Bathes were vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed away, &amp; hee found no Treasure. The poore folk perceiuing that, were all sorrowfull, saying, cursed might he be for euermore, that for his singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler couetousnesse hath destroyed this Image, and hath robbed vs of so gret solace and comfort: heereafter assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled three Kinges, the which of the Romaynes had beene oppressed, and suffered great wrongs, and went to Counsell with them of their Counsel, how they might best of the Romains be auenged, and some of them sayd, we labour in vaine; as long as there standeth the tower with the Images we may doe nothing against them.</p>
               <p>To the Counsaile arose vp Foure Knights and said to the Kinges, we haue thought on a good remedie, how ye shall destroye the Tower with the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:51"/> Images, &amp; that to doe and bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, wee will our liues set to pledge it that you will do the cost. Then said the King, what cost shall we do? they sayd, we must haue foure Tunnes of Gou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Then said the King, take the Gold and fulfill your promise: the Knights tooke the Gould and went towardes Roome, and when they were thether come, in the night with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out one of the Gates, in the Ditch with water they drowned one of the Tunnes with the Gold, and another tun they drouned by the second gate, and the third Tun they drowned by the third gate, &amp; the fourth tun by the fourth gate they drowned: and when they had this done, early in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they entred into the Cittie at an houre conuenient when the Emperor went ouer to the Mart, and did him reuerence as it behoued The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour seeing them, demaunded from whence they were, of what science, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178576:52"/> what Seruice they could doe: they answered, wee are of farre Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and Soothsayers so perfect, that there was neuer thing so priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and secretly hid, but that we shall finde it by our dreames. Wee haue heard that yee labour and haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in such thinges, and therefore came we vnto you to know if yee had any need of our seruice. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour sayd, I shall prooue you, and if it be so that I finde you true, you shall haue of me great rewards &amp; thanks. They sayd, we aske nothing for our lobours, but the halfe deale of the Gould that by vs shall bee found: the Emperour sayd, I am very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and thus they had with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour many words. At euen when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperour was going to bed, they said vnto him, My lord if it please you this night shall the oldest of vs set his cunning a worke, and dreame the thirde day wee shall shew you his
<pb facs="tcp:178576:52"/> dreame, and what it signifieth: the Emperor said, go in gods name. And they went forth with great gladnes, and all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> night they passed ouer with much ioy and mirth, vpon trust that they should come to a good purpose. When the third day was come, they went early to the Emperour, the first of them said, my Lord, please it you to goe with vs without one of the gates of the Cittie, and I shall shew you where a tun full of gould is hid, the Emperour sayd I shall goe with you and see if it be true that you say. When they were come to the place, they drew out the runne that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there hadde put, the Emperour when hee sawe that was glad, and gaue to them their part. Then sayd the second Dreamer, My Lord, this night shall I dreame: the Emperour sayd, God giue you a good Dreame. The next night came, and he tooke out the other Tun, and gaue it to the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:53"/> Emperour, and tooke also his share, in like wise did the third &amp; the fourth, vppon the which the Emperour was out of all measure ioyous &amp; glad, and sayd, he had not seene afore such true &amp; expert Soothsayers or Dreamers as they were, then sayd they altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at once, as it had been out of one mouth. My Lord, we haue one after another dreamed, the which as yee haue seen they be al true prooued, but nowe if it please you that wee may Dreame all together this night, wee trust that to vs shalbe shewed where we shall finde a great quantitie and substance of Golde and of riches: the Emperour sayd, God giue to you a good dreame, which to me and to you may be profitable. On the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row they came againe vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and said to him with ioyous and glad Visages and countenances My Lord, we bring good and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table tydings, for this night in our
<pb facs="tcp:178576:53"/> sleepes, such &amp; so great Treasure is to vs shewed, the which if you will suffer it to be sought, you shall bee so much inriched, that in this World shall bee none lyke you: the Emperor sayd, where should wee finde this Treasure? they sayd vnder the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Tower that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Images stand vppon. The Emperour answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, God defēd that I should for loue of gold destroy y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Tower with Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherewith wee of our enemies yee defended and warned: they sayd to him againe, My Lord, haue yee found vs in our sayinges otherwise than true and rightfull. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayd, nay: O Lord sayd they, we with our owne handes shall giue out the Gould, without hurting of the Tower or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Images. And it is expedient, that secretly in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> night, by vs it bee done, for dread of resort, &amp; concourse of the people, least that ye should run in the noise and clamours
<pb facs="tcp:178576:54"/> of them, and also that they should not take that good gold away from you and vs. The Emperour said, goe in the name of god and doe your best, as you well can, and I shall to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row early come to you. Then went they with ioy and gladnesse, &amp; in the night they were let into the Tower, and with great hast &amp; diligence they vndermined it, and in the next day early they mounted vppon their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and rode againe towardes their owne Country with ioy and glory, &amp; ere that they came without the sight of Rome, the Tower fell down on the morning ensuing. When it was fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len &amp; the Senators it perceiued, they sorrowed greatly, and there was great bewailing throughout all the Citie, and they went to the Emperor and said, lord how may it be that this tower is thus fallen, by the which we haue always had warning afore of our enemies: he answered and said,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:54"/> to me came foure false deceiuers, and fayned themselues to be Soothsay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and that they could finde Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure in the ground. And they sayd, that vnder the foundation of the Tower was hidden an innumerable Summe of Gould, the which they should vndermine without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urting of the Tower or the Images, and I gaue faith to them, and they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued mee. They answered him. ye haue coueted so much Gould, and for your saciate couetousnesse, wee shall be all destroyed, but first your coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse shall fall vppon your selfe: they took and led him to the Capitol, and layd him on his back and poured his mouth full of moulten gould, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, you haue desired gold, and therfore ye shall drinke gold, and after they buried him quicke. Not long after that, came the enemies against the Romaynes, and ouercame &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed them all. Then said the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb facs="tcp:178576:55"/> vnto the Emperor, haue ye my Lord this Example well vnderstood, and he said, right well: then said she, the Tower with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Images is your body and Fiue witts. As long as you doe liue, there is none so hardy to trouble or make warre vpon you, nor vpon your people, that hath your son right well vnderstood, who with his seuen Maisters, and with their false narrations of Fables, seek how they may destroy you: for you are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much couetous to heare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to them, and insomuch that they shall vndermine you, and cast you vnder foot and bring you to nought. The Images are your fiue Witts, that be all lost. And for as much as you bee so Childish and foolish, they shall destroye and slay you, and your Son shal obtaine your Empire. The Emperour said, ye haue recited to me a good example, wherefore it shal not happen to me as it did with the tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:55"/> but my Sonne first this day shall bee hanged, to whome the Empresse said, if ye doe so, ye shall fare well, and liue long. Vppon the third day, hee commaunded him to be led to hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as he was led towards the Gallowes, came riding against him vppon an Horse, his Fift Maister to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Pallace, and came before the Emperour, and saluted him with all reuerence, and he despised his sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation, and put him in feare of his life. And the Maister said, My lord I haue not deserued to die, and for to despise my salutatiō, it is not for your honour, for your Son hath not with vs been of such conditions as yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute him, as yee in short time shall finde: &amp; that he speaketh not is of his great wisdome, &amp; know ye y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shall well speake as time cometh, though that hee now speaketh not, as you in short time shall heare: but ye say that hee would haue shamed your Wife,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:56"/> that belieue not, for so a wise man as he is, should neuer attempt so shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a deed, and if ye put him to death for your wiues wordes, yee should not escape without shame and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance like as <hi>Ippocras</hi> scaped not with out vengeance for the death of <hi>Galie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his Cozen: the Emperour sayd, that would I faine heare and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. Then said the Maister, what should availe to tell you this narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for your profite if in the mean sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son your Sonne shall die, &amp; therefore if ye will call again your Son, it shall be done at your pleasure, and after do as you thinke best. The Emperour bad call againe his Sonne, &amp; set him in prison: and then began the Maister to tell on this manner as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the fift Maister.</head>
               <p>SOmetime there was a famous Phisition named <hi>Ippocras,</hi> right cunning, the which excelled all
<pb facs="tcp:178576:56"/> other in cunning and Science, hee had with him his Nephewe or Kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was called <hi>Galienus,</hi> the which hee loued much: this <hi>Galienus</hi> was of an excellent wit, and applyed all his minde and wit to learne of his vncle the Science of Phisicke. When <hi>Ippocras</hi> perceiued that, in as much as he could, he hid from him his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, fearing that hee should excell him in that Craft for the great witte that hee was of. As <hi>Galienus</hi> sawe this, hee studied and excercised, in so much that in short time hee had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Cunning in Phisicke, for the which <hi>Ippocras</hi> enuyed him much. It happened vppon a time thereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> send his Messenger vnto <hi>Ippocras,</hi> that hee should come vnto him for to cure his Sonne: <hi>Ippocras</hi> excused himselfe and would not goe, but sent his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen <hi>Galienus</hi> with his Letters of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuse for his not comming. And when
<pb facs="tcp:178576:57"/>
                  <hi>Galienus</hi> was come before the king, hee was right worshipfully recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but they maruailed why that <hi>Ippocras</hi> would not come, hee excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him, saying, that hee had many great thinges to doe, and hee might not come, but hee hath sent mee in his stead, and with the helpe of God I shall make whole the Childe, that pleased very well the King. <hi>Galienus</hi> went to the Childe, and when he had seene his Vrine, and tasted his poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, hee sayd to the Queene, O excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Princesse, I pray you heare and suffer my wordes, and tell mee who is the Father of the Child? shee sayd, who should be his father but my lord the King? <hi>Galienus</hi> sayd, I am sure that hee is not the Father, shee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, if ye will say that for a troth, I shall cause your head to bee smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off: he answered, I say once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that this King is not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:57"/> and I am not therefore come hether to loose my head, for I haue not deserued any such reward, and so was going his way. The Queene spake, O good Maister <hi>Galienus,</hi> if yee will keepe it secret, and not disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mee, I shall shew and open vnto you my heart. The Master said, God defend that from mee, that I to any person should shewe it, and therefore O noble Queene shew it boldly to me, for it shall neuer passe my mouth, and afterwards I shall ease &amp; make your Son whole: shee sayd, if ye doe that, ye shall haue a good reward of mee, &amp; therefore heare what I shall say. By fortune came hither vnto my Lord, the King of Burgundie, and he was so long conuersant with me, that this child by him I bare: then said the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, feare ye not, I knew that it was so before, and anon he gaue the Child to eate beefe, or of an Oxe, and drink, and the Child was ease of his infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:58"/> And when as the King heard that the child was quite of his mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, he gaue vnto the Maister a good reward, but of the Queene hee secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued a great guift and a special thanke, and so went this way. And when that hee was come home, <hi>Ippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras</hi> his Maister demaunded of him saying, haue ye beheld the Child? and he sayd yea, then asked he him what he gaue him, flesh or beefe to eate, and water to drinke. Then sayd <hi>Ippocras</hi> the woman of the Child is not true to her husband, that is troth said <hi>Gelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> then <hi>Ippocras</hi> was mooued with enuie, and thought in himselfe, if here be not found a remedie, my Science shall no more be let by, and he shall be named and praised aboue mee. And from that day forward, he bethought him and deuised how hee might saly him. Vpon a day <hi>Ippocras</hi> called him and sayd, come go we to seeke and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hearbs in the Garden, to whom
<pb facs="tcp:178576:58"/> hee sayd, Maister I am readye: and when they were come into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, <hi>Ippocras</hi> sayd, I feele that this hearbe is right vertuous, stoop down &amp; gather me of it, <hi>Galienus</hi> did so. As they went about the Garden, said <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocras,</hi> now I well perceiue the odour of this hearbe, that it is better ande preciouser than Gould. and therefore stoope downe to the ground, &amp; draw him out with the roots, for it is much worth: <hi>Galinues</hi> bowed downe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to pul vp the hearb, and <hi>Ippocras</hi> drewe out his knife and killed him, After that, <hi>Ippocras</hi> fell sicke to death, that the strength of his bodie fayled him, and did as much as hee could to helpe himselfe, but it would not be, and as the Schollers and Disciples heard of it, they went hastily to him, and all that they might or could doe, for the profite of his health, they did, but it auailed him nothing.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Ippocras</hi> this perceiued,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:59"/> he said vnto his Schollers, goe fetch me a great Tun, and fill it full vnto the brinkes with water, and when they had so done, he sayd vnto them, make now therein a hundred holes, and when that was also done, there went none of the water out. Then said <hi>Ippocras,</hi> behould my most deere Disciples how that the vengeance of God is fallen vppon mee, as ye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly may see, for in this Tunne are an hundred holes, &amp; yet goeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out not one drop: right so there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth no vertue out of the hearbes to helpe me, and therefore what you doe vnto me helpeth not, for I must die: but my deere children, if my Nephew <hi>Galienus</hi> were now aliue, hee could heale mee, whome I haue slaine, and that greueth mee sore, and therefore the vengeance of God commeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon mee. And this sayd, hee turned him to the wall &amp; gaue vp the Ghost. Then said the Master vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:59"/> my Lord vnderstand yee well what I haue sayd, hee answered, yea right well, what hurt had it beene to him, if <hi>Galienus</hi> had liued?</p>
               <p>The Master answered, it had been right good for <hi>Ippocras</hi> at that time, had not he dyed, &amp; therefore by right wise iudgement of god, his medicines auailed him not, &amp; therefore I shewed to you, that it shall happen worse to you, if that you put to death your son for the wordes of your Wife, who in time of necessitie shall assist and suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour you: and consider ye not, that ye haue after your first wife wedded this wife that ye now haue, and so ye may the third and fourth, and neuer shall ye haue of any of them such a Sonne that shall keepe and saue you from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill? the Emperour sayd, truely he shall not die.</p>
               <p>Then sayd the Maister, then doe ye wisely, and I commēd you to God and I thanke you, that yee haue this
<pb facs="tcp:178576:60"/> day for me spared your son. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayd, I marke this well, that women are craftie and subtill, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will not for you, but for my selfe, saue him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sixt Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>WHen as the Empresse had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, shee shewed her selfe so froward &amp; impattēt a body, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that sawe her or heard her, wondr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and sayd to the Emperour, your wife she pineth her selfe, as thogh she wold die. The Emperour hearing thereof, went ot her and said, wherefore bee yee so impatient? she answered, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, O Lord how should I hold it in when I am the onely Daughter of a King, &amp; your wife? &amp; in your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie I haue had a great dispight and shame, &amp; continually yee haue promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed me to punish him, but ye performe it not. The Emperor said, I wor not what I shall doe? ye labour from day
<pb facs="tcp:178576:61"/> to day to haue my Sonne to die: and the Maisters labour to saue his life: and amongest all these I know well that he is my Sonne, but where the troth is that I know not. Then said she, this is the cause whereof I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that ye beleeue the Maisters, more than you do me, therefore it shal happen to you as it did to a king with his Steward. Then sayd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, tel that example, peraduenture it may mooue me the sooner to put my sonne to death: she sayd gladly, but I pray you giue attendance to what I shall say, and began to tell as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ensueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The sixt Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>THere was a king right proud &amp; maruailously deformed in his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage, in such wise, that women hated and abhorred him.</p>
               <p>This King thought to destroy Rome and to slay y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Romaines, and to take
<pb facs="tcp:178576:62"/> and carrie away the bodies of Peter and Paule: who while hee was in this minde, called to him his Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward that was right secret with him of his priuie councell, and said to him, goe and seeke me a faire woman, that this night may sleep with mee. The Steward answered, My Lord, yee knowe well you infirmitie and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, and that no woman will doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill without a great summe of mony. The King said, think ye that for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I will want one? Haue I not Gold and siliuer ynough? though it were a M. florens, I would it glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue. The Steward hearing that, was anon smitten with couetousnes, &amp; went to his owne wife which was right faire and chast, &amp; of good kindred, and said to her, O my good Wife, my Lord desireth &amp; coueteth for to sleepe with a faire and beautifull woman, and will not forbeare it, though that she should aske of him a M. florens,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:62"/> and hath commaunded me to prouide him of one, and therefore I counsaile you, that ye to vs get this money: the wife said, were it not so that the King were so proud and foule of visage, yet would I not to that euill consent, for the sin against God. The Steward answered, I consent that ye shall doe it, and thereto I counsaile and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund you, &amp; promise you, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out yee consent to me herein, yee shall neuer haue good day with mee: shee hearing that trembled, insomuch that for dread shee consented to him.</p>
               <p>The Steward then went to the King &amp; sayd, Sir, I haue found out a faire woman, and she is come of a verie good house, which will not lesse haue than a M. Florens, and in the Euening shee shall come, and early in the Morning she must away, that she be not seen of the people: the King an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered and said, I am well content. When the night was come, the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:178576:63"/> led his Wife to the Kings bed, &amp; made fast the dore &amp; went his way: early in the Morning the Steward arose and went to the King and sayd, My Lord, it will bee day within a while, it is good that you perfourme your promise, and let the woman go: the King said, this woman pleaseth me so well, that so soone shee shall not depart from me. When he heard that, hee departed thence all sorrie, vniteth he tarried any while, but came to the King againe and said, my lord y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is come, therefore let the woman go as I haue promised her, least that she be ashamed: the King said, yet shal she not goe from me, &amp; therfore go out &amp; shut the dore again. The Steward right sorrowfull departed, and went vp and downe with an heauie and an angry heart, till that the faire and the cleare day appeared, and then he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againe into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chamber &amp; said, my lord it is cleare day, suffer the woman
<pb facs="tcp:178576:60"/> to depart, that shee be not therewith ashamed. The King answered, I say to you for a troth, shee shall not yet depart, for her companie is vnto mee right pleasant and acceptable. The Steward hearing that, could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger forbeare nor hold his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell but said to the King, O my good and gracious Lord I beseech you suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her to depart, for it is my owne Wife the King hearing that, sayd to him, open the window. And when it was open, the faire and bright day appeared, he beheld the woman right faire &amp; goodly, and perceiued that it was the wife of the Steward, &amp; sayd to him, O thou most worst Ribaud or knaue, why hast thou for so little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney shamed and vndone thy good and faire wife, and her hast deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me vnwitting? therefore hast thee and get thee gone out of my Realme, and neuer more hereafter come in my sight, for from henceforth, if euer I
<pb facs="tcp:178576:61"/> may see thee, thou shalt die the most shamefull and horriblest death that euer can be imagined. When the Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heard that, he fled his way, and durst not abide, &amp; was neuer so hardy any more to come into the Realme. And the King kept that Wife all his life time in great worship, &amp; gaue to her plentie of all thinges that to her behooued and pertained.</p>
               <p>After that, the King caused to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and assembled a great &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Armie of puissant men of warre, and so he went to Roome with great might, and besieged the Cittie on all sides, so long vntill the Romaynes would haue deliuered him for to haue departed and withdrawne himselfe from thence, the bodies of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles Peter and Paule.</p>
               <p>Then was there in the Citie seuen wise Masters as ye haue now, by the councell of whome all the Citie was guided and gouerned. And the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens
<pb facs="tcp:178576:63"/> came to them and said, what shall we doe? it behooueth vs that we deliuer vnto your deadly enemies, the bodies of the holy Apostles, or else the Citie. Then answered the first Maister, I shall with my wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and cunning this day saue the Citie, and the bodies of the Apostles, and so one after nother promised to doe the same: and so euerie of them for one day, in like wise as the Maisters haue promised your Son. With that the King began to assault the Citie on all parts: then began the first Master to say and alleadge so wisely for to haue peace, that the King that day left his assault, and withdrew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a little from the Citie, and so did all the Maisters one after another, till the last. Vnto whom came the Burgesses &amp; say, O Maister ye shal vnderstand that the King hath made his oath sworn, that to morrow with all his puissance and strength hee wil
<pb facs="tcp:178576:64"/> haue &amp; win the Citie, or else we must all be in ieopardie to loose our liues: therfore in acquiting of your promise, defend and keepe vs from daunger, like as all our Fellowes before you haue hone. Then answered the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and sayd, be of good comfort and feare not, for to morrow I shall by my cunning shew such a worke and operation, that the King with all his puissance and might shall flye away &amp; leaue the Siege. The next day the king made &amp; gaue great assault vnto the Citie: then went the Master and cloathed himselfe with maruaylous straunge vesture, hauing therein the feathers or the tayles of Peacockes, and of other Fowles of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and tooke two bright swords in each hand one, and went therwith and stood vpon the highest Tower of all the City, and began to moone and turne of shewe himselfe about on all parts towards the Host, so that they
<pb facs="tcp:178576:64"/> might all behold and see him: and he held in his mouth the twoo bright Swords that maruailously shyned, they without of the Kings Host that beholding, sayd to him, O Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold vpon the hyest of yonder towers a wounderful thing or a figure, yea I see it well that it is maruailous, but what it is I know not, they sayd, it is Iesus the God of Christian folke, that is come out of heauen vs to slay and destroy with his two swords, if we any longer abide. The King hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that, trembled for feare, and said what shall we doe? there is but one way, and that is, that we anon goe and depart frō hence, least that their God avenge himselfe vppon vs: then began the King with all his Host to lye: notwithstanding there was no need, but that they of the master were beguiled &amp; deceiued. And whē the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines</hi> saw that, they hastily pursued after, all armed in good ordinance, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178576:65"/> the King with many of his people they killed and destroyed, and also in that manner by great subtiltie of the Maister was the mightie King with his Armie subdued. Then said the Empresse to the Emperour, Lord ye haue vnderstood what I haue said, he say yea, verie well in the best wise. She sayd, now yee haue heard what I haue sayd to you at the beginning of this narration of the steward that the King trusted so much, which for couetousnes of gold shamed his own wife, and he for that was driuen and banished out of the Land: In like manner your Son for the desire &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perite that he hath to the Empire, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to confound and destroy you. But whiles you be in your might and power, doe with him as the King did with his Steward: if yee will not put him to death, banish him out of your Empire, that yee without feare may liue in suerty of your life. And
<pb facs="tcp:178576:65"/> haue ye not also heard, how the King lay before the Citie of ROme, and how he was by the wise Masters deceiued &amp; scorned, that he with his folke were killed and slaine? In the same wise the seuen Masters intend to do with you, and by their false wiles and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties to deceiue you, and in the end to slay you, that your son may raigne. Whereupon answered the Emperor, and sayd, that shall not so be, for my son to morow shall die. Then he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his seruants that they should lead his son to hanging. When the people heard that, there was a great noise and gathering of them, together bewayling the death of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Sonne: and as the sixt Maister heard that, he hasted him to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and saluted him honourably, but hee tooke it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nthankefully, and threatned him that hee should die with his Sonne, for that hee was with them made dumme, and a Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baud,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:66"/> which was shewed towards his Wife. The Maister sayd, I haue not deserued to die with your Son, but to haue great and large gifts, for he is not dum, as ye shall heare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three dayes if he may liue so long: But if you put him to death for the words of your wife, then shall I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile at your wisedome, and without doubt it shall happen to you, as some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it happened to a Knight that to much allowed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sayings of his Wife, that he was bound to an Horse tayle, and drawne throughout all the Citie to the gallowes. The Emperor sayd for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> loue of God shew me that exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that I may the better beware of that perill: that will I not doe sayd the Maisters, without you doe call a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine your son: then he commaunded to call his Sonne, and the Maister began as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the sixt Maister.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:66"/>
               <p>SOmetime there was an Emperor of Rome which had three knights whome hee loued aboue all other. And in the same Cittie was an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Knight, that had wedded a faire young Wife, as you doe the Empres, which aboue all other things hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: this Ladie could sing right well and melodiously, &amp; with such sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, that many drew to her house, and desired her companye. It befell vpon a season, as she sat at her house, her Visage turned into the Street, that she might see thē that went by, and began sweetly to sing, that all folke delighted to heare her. By chaunce came that wayes a Knight of the Emperours Court, that heard her voyce, and beholding her atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, hee was taken inher loue, and entred into her house, and fell in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with her of loue, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all other talke he demaunded what hee should giue her to sleepe by
<pb facs="tcp:178576:67"/> her one night, she answered, an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Florens. The Knight said, tell mee when I shall come, &amp; I will giue you an hundred Florens. She said, when I haue conuenient time I shall send for you: the next day shee sang againe in the same, place and it fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the second Knight of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to come by that same way, the which likewise was smitten in her loue, and he also promised her a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Florens. To whome also shee promised to shewe him a time proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The third day was the third Knight in like wise caught in her loue, the which also promised her an Hundred Florens, and shee to giue him knowledge of the time. These three Knights haue so secretly spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with the Ladie, that none of them had knowledge of other. The Ladie that was malicious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, came to her Husband, and sayd, Sir I haue a secret matter to
<pb facs="tcp:178576:67"/> shew you, wherein if you follow my counsaile, our necessitie and pouerty ye may largely relieue. The Knight sayd, tell it me, &amp; I will hold it secret, and fulfill it to my power: shee sayd, Three Knights of the Emperours Court haue been with me one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, in such wise, that none know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of anothers councell, &amp; euerie one hath offered me a C. Florens: might we three C. Florens get, &amp; no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof detected, should it not be to vs a great helpe, and our poue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be well releiued? The Knight said forsooth yes, &amp; therfore whatsoeuer you counsaile me to doe, I shall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. Then sayd shee, I shall giue you this counsaile, when they come with the florens, ye shal stand behind the gate with your Sword drawne in your hand, and because that euery of them cometh alone, ye shall slay one after another, &amp; so wee shall haue the 3. C. Florens of them without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:178576:68"/> of any other. The Knight an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, O my best beloued Wife, I feare me that this euill cannot be hid, and wee should therecore shamefully suffer death if that it were knowne. She sayd I shall this worke begin, and I shall make thereof a good end, and feare it not when the Knight saw that shee was so hardy, it caused him to be the more bold, and shee sent for the first Knight, and hee came to her anon without any tarrying, to the gate and knocked, and she asked if he brought the C. Florens, &amp; he said yea, I haue them heere already, then let shee him in, and anon in the entring in her husband killed him, and so hee did the second, and the third, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one secret Chamber they drewe the bodies of them. When it was thus done, the Knight sayd vnto his Ladie: O deere Wife, if these bodies be found with vs, wee shall die the most shamefull death that can bee
<pb facs="tcp:178576:68"/> imagined, for it is not possible but that these Knights shall bee missed in the Emperours Court, and great search and inquisition shall bee for them made throughout all this City, where they are become. She sayd, sir I haue this worke begun, &amp; shall make thereof a good end, feare not as aforesayde. This Ladie had a Brother, the which had the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the wealth of the Citie, that on the nights watched in the streetes with his fellowes, shee stood at her gate and called her brother and sayd, O my best Brother, I haue a secret matter, the which in confession I shall shewe you, and therefore come a little within: and whē that he was come in, the Lady receiued him frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and gaue him Wine to drinke and sayd, my welbeloued brother, this is the cause that I haue called you, for I haue much neede of your counsaile. The Brother answered, say it bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:178576:69"/> vnto mee, and whatsoeuer that I maye doe, to my power, that shall be at your desire without letting: then sayd shee, yesterday came in a Knight in good friendship, but afterwardes hee fell into such words and variance with my husband, that hee slew him, and he lyeth in my Chamber: &amp; mine one deere brother, we haue no man that we may trust but you, and if the bodie be found by vs, wee should die; she made mention but of one, the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther said, deliuer him me in a sacke, &amp; I shall beare him to the sea: she hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that, was full glad thereof, and deliuered vnto him the body of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first Knight, he took it and went withall a good pace &amp; cast him therein. And as this was done he came againe to his sister and said, giue me now of the best wine, for you are of him quit, and she thanked him &amp; went into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as though she had gone for wine, and began to crie with an high voyce,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:69"/> the Knight that was cast into the sea is come againe: as her brother heard that, he woundred sore and said, giue me him I shall see if he will rise again, &amp; took the bodie of the second Knight, supposing it had beene of the first Knight, &amp; went to the sea, &amp; with a great stone he drowned him therin: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> done, he went againe vnto his sisters house and said, now fill me a cup with good wine, for I haue drowned him so deepe, that hee shall neuer come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, she sayd thanks be to God, and went again to her Chamber, &amp; fained her to fetch Wine, &amp; cryed with a loud voice, alas woe be to me, he is risen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and come out of the Sea: &amp; as her brother heard that, with a great maruaile said, what Diuil is this Knight that I haue cast into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; notwithstanding is come again? deliuer me him the third time, and I shall see if he will come againe: then gaue she him the third Knight, which
<pb facs="tcp:178576:70"/> hee belieued had been the first Knight and wēt without the Citie to a great Forrest, &amp; made a great fier &amp; cast the knight therein, and when he was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most burnt, the Brother went thence a little distance to doe his neede, then came there a Knight that would ride to the Citie, where in the Morning they should haue a tourney &amp; Iusting, and it was cold weather &amp; darke, he was not far from the Citie, and when he had a sight of fier, he drew thereto, and lighted from his horse and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him. The watchman came and sayd to him, what art thou? y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knight sayd, I am a gentle Knight: then spake the watchman &amp; sayd, thou art no knight but a Diuel, for first I cast thee into the water, the second time with a great stone I drowned thee, &amp; the third time I haue put thee in this fier supposing thou hadst been burnt, and yet thou standest here, &amp; then he tooke the knight with his horse, and
<pb facs="tcp:178576:70"/> cast them both into the fier. After that he went againe to his sister and tolde what had happened him, &amp; said, now bring mee of the best Wine, for after that I had burnt him, I found him againe be the fier with a horse, and I haue cast them both in the fier, and by this his sister perceiued well that hee had burnt a Knight of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> turney: who anon brought him of the best wine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly, &amp; after he had wel drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he went thence. Not long time after there fell a great debate &amp; contē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt the knight and his wife in such wise that hee smote her, which had indignation thereof, and waxed angrie &amp; sayd that many might heare it, O wretch wilt thou kill mee, as thou hast done the three Knights of the Emperors? certain men that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, laid hand on thē, &amp; brought thē before the Emperor, and the woman confessed that her husband and had slaine three Knights of the emperors, &amp; how
<pb facs="tcp:178576:71"/> he took from them three C. Florens. And as it was thus in troth found, both were drawn at an horse tayle, &amp; hanged vpon a gallowes. Then said the Maister to the Emperour, haue you vnderstood what I haue sayd? Hee answered, right well, I say for certaine, that Wife was the worst woman that might be of all women; for first she mooued and stirred him vp to murder, and afterward discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him. The Maister sayd, without doubt it shall happen to you worse, if you put to death your Sonne by the aduise of your Wife. The Emperor sayd, My Son shall not die this day, The Maister hearing that, gaue thankes to the Emperour and tooke leaue, and went this way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Seauenth Complaint of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>WHen the Empresse heard that the Son of the Emperor was yet liuing: as a mad woman shee ran
<pb facs="tcp:178576:71"/> to the Emperour weeping and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, saying, O vnhappy woman, alas what shall I doe? I must needs slay my self that am so shamed, and no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment therevpon done: the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour answered, God defend, that you should haue mind on such things, but suffer a while &amp; you shall haue a good end of your cause. She answered, sir the end shall be euill, for of that shall follow to you and to mee great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion. the Emperour sayd, leaue of such talke, she said, Lord it shall come to you and your Son as it happened to a King and to his Steward. The Emperour sayd, I pray you tell mee that example, she sayd, I will glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell it, but I feare mee that yee will heare me no more: For the next day, the seuenth Maister shall speake and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue you Son from the death as his fellowes haue done. And the next day after that, your Sonne shall speake, of whose wordes you shall haue and
<pb facs="tcp:178576:72"/> take such ioy and delectation, that the loue betwixt vs shall bee wholly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten and washed away. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour said that it is impossible to me, for I shall neuer forget your loue.</p>
               <p>Then said she, O my best beloued Lord, if it please you I will tell you one example, by the which ye shall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware before of many perills to come, and especially of your accursed Son, who intendeth to destroy me by his Maisters: the Emperour sayd, tell on you example: and the Empresse began to tell of this ensuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Seuenth Example of the Empresse.</head>
               <p>THere was sometime a King, the which loued his Wife aboue all things, insomuch that he closed her in a strong Castle, and hee bare the keyes of the Castle himselfe, the Ladie was therfore right heauie, and desolate. Now in farre parts there was a valiant knight, the which
<pb facs="tcp:178576:72"/> in the night dreamed after this effect: He thought that hee sawe one of the fairest Queenes that might be, whose loue aboue all thinges hee desired to obtaine, and that if hee might see her walking, he should cleerely haue knowledge of her, by whom toward him a great friendship and worship should come. To the Queene that same night by vision of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said knight, the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> was also shewed, &amp; yet they had of each other no knowledge of name, neither of fame: When the knight had thus dreamed and seen in his sleepe, he thought and determined in his mind, that his foot should not rest, vntill the time he had found that Ladie that to him was shewed in his dreame: and so tooke his Horse, and with him all that was necessarie for his iourney, and rode &amp; went through diuers Regions and Landes, so long, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at the last hee came vnto the same L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd where that Queene was by
<pb facs="tcp:178576:73"/> her husband closed &amp; kept in a strong Castle. And when this said Knight was come into the same Citie, and by a certain season had therein soiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: it happened vppon a day as the Knight walked by the Castle, and knew not then that the Queene was therein, shee fate in a window to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and see the people going by, and among all other shee sawe the same Knight, and knew that hee was the same man that shee had dreaned off: and the Knight by chance lift vp his eyes, and perceiued the Ladie sitting in the window, &amp; anon his mind gaue him, that it was shee of whome hee had dreamed, and she began to sing a song of loue. And as he heard that, hee was anon taken with her loue: the Knight from thencefoorth dayly went &amp; walked about the castle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding it all ouer, if any manner of way hee might get to shew her his mind. The Lady perceiuing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg>, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:73"/> Letter and cast it downe to him. And when he had read ouer y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Letter, and vnderstood the will of the Ladie, hee began to haunt Iusts and Tourna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and so did many great and maruailous acts, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fame of him came to the King. And as the King heard thereof, he sent after him &amp; sayd to him, Sir knight, I haue heard much honour of you, if it will please you to abide and dwell with vs, wee shall giue you large gifts &amp; rewards. The knight answered and sayd, O right mightie Prince, I am your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, would to God that I could doe any seruice to please your Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence without taking of any reward, saue one thing before all other I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire. The king sayd, shew it vnto me boldly what thing it is: the knight answered, My Lord sithence it hath pleased your Maiestie to take me for your Seruant and one of your noble Councell, me semeth that it were very
<pb facs="tcp:178576:74"/> expedient for both our solaces, that I had a place nigh vnto the wall of the Castle, that I might at all times bee the more ready at your calling when you haue need. Then the King said, I consent to you, make it as ye thinke best. Then went the Knight and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red workemen and made a faire lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging by the wales of the Tower, and when it was all ready, he made a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant with a workman for to make out of his house a secret way into the Court: and when it was made ready after his intent, he killed the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man because he should not discouer it, and so went in to the Queen, and did to her reuerence accordingly, &amp; they talked of many thinges, that at the end he desired to sleepe by her, which she oftentimes denyed, but neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse she consented to him. After that, the Queen thought, what shall I do? if I should giue knowledge thereof vnto my husband, therof would come
<pb facs="tcp:178576:74"/> two euils: the one is my shame, and that peraduenture hee should vtterly forsake mee, and driue mee out of his land for euer: and the other is, the Knight he would slay, for from death he could not escape, and therefore it is better that I be stil, and tell not. The Knight after that, as often as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him, went in to the Queene, &amp; did his will with her, and shee gaue him a Ring, the which the King had giuen to her at her wedding. This knight in euery battell and tournament had the Victory, wherefore hee was and stoode in great fauour with the king, so that hee made him his Steward, and Gouernour of all his Region and land. It happened vppon a day that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> king disposed himselfe to goe on hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and commanded his Steward to make him ready on the Morrowe for to goe with him, whereto he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himselfe all ready. And vpon the Morrow after they entred into the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:75"/> forrest, &amp; all this day they chased and followed the wild beasts, that they were so weary, that the King sat him downe by a Fountain to rest, and the knight by the King, and fell on sleepe by him, hauing the ring vpon his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the which the King marked, and knewe. After that the Knight percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that the King had seene the ring, fayned him sore sicke, and sayd. My Lord, I feele my selfe so sore sicke, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> if I doe not hastily find some remedie therefore by the meanes of Phisicke, I am but a dead man, and therefore I pray you giue me leaue for to goe home, vnto whome he sayd, goe my deere friend in Gods name: he anon god vpō his horse, &amp; hasted him to his house and went to the queene, and gaue her againe the Ring, and tould her how the King had marked it and seene it on his finger, and prayed her if he made any question of the Ring, that she should shew it to him. This
<pb facs="tcp:178576:75"/> done, hee went downe againe to his lodging: and anon after, the King came to the Queene, and shee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him right louingly, and after that a little time was passed, the king said, my Ladye shewe me where the Ring is that I gaue to you, I desire to see it, shee sayd O my Lord, to what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent at this time desire you to see it? then said he, if ye shew it not to me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent, it shall repent you: then she rose vp &amp; went to her chest, &amp; brought the Ring to the King, &amp; when he sawe it, he was halfe ashamed, and said vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her: O howe like is the Knightes Ring to this Ring, which I sawe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his finger, and I beleeued that it had been mine, and therfore that was the cause why I asked it so hastily of you. And of this ill suspicion I yeld my selfe guiltie against you my deere ladie in this behalfe, for the strēgth of the tower deceiued me, for I thought that no man might come therein
<pb facs="tcp:178576:76"/> but I my selfe alone: Shee sayd, my deere Lord wonder not, for one Ring is like another, and workemen make fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dome any woorke, but that other make the same, but god forgiue it you that you haue suspected me, when you know the strength of the Tower, and the keyes you haue alwaies by you, &amp; will trust no man therewith. After that the Knight ordained a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, and said to the King, my Lord it is so that my Lady and Loue is come out of my Countrey, and I haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d a Diuer to be made, and I would pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y you that at this time ye will doe we honour, and take such meat as is in my house. The King said, I shall gladly doe to you that worshippe and more. The Knight was glad thereof, and by his secret way went to the Queene and said vnto her, my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die thus doe, you shall come to my house by my priuie way, and cloath you in rich cloathing, after the maner
<pb facs="tcp:178576:76"/> of my Country, and you shal sit at the table wich my king as my soueraigne Ladie, and make him good cheere: she sayd, as you will I shall all things fulfill. And when the houre of meat was come, and King from the Castle was commin towardes the Knights house, in the meane time the Queene entred by the secret way into the knights lodging, and apparelled her after the manner of the knights Countrey, and when the King was entred into the house, she saluted and receiued him reuerently, and when that the King had beholden her, hee demaunded of the Knight what wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is this so faire: then the knight sayd, my Lord it is my Soueraigne Ladie that nowe is come out of my Country after me, I haue taried long in her seruice, then the Knight set the King at the table as it behooued, and made the Queene to sit by him, and the King thought that it was his
<pb facs="tcp:178576:77"/> Queene and said within himselfe, O how like is this woman vnto my wife? so the strength of the Tower deceiued him, that he gaue more faith and credence to the Knights words, than he did to his owne eyes. The Queene began to speake and talke to the king, and to stirre him to eat and drinke and make good cheere, and as the King heard her voice, then he said vnto himselfe, O blessed Lord, how like is this woman to my queene in her behauiour, speech, visage, and in all other things and conditions? and alway the strength of the Tower fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him. In the end of the feast, the Knight prayed his Loue to sing a song before the king, and shee began to sing a song of Loue: When hee heard that, hee knew her voyce, and thought, is not this my wife? how may it be she, haue not I the keyes of the Tower my selfe in keeping? and so all the meat time he sate and stroue
<pb facs="tcp:178576:77"/> within himselfe, then at the last hee sayd vnto the Knight that hee should take vp the Table, for hee had some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for to doe, for he was in great thought and sore troubled in mind. The Knight answered and said, my Lord ye make no good cheere, yeare full of thoughts: and if it pleause you wee shall make to you some sport and solace. And the woman said, please it you sir King here by vs to tarrie, wee shall make to you all the sport and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace that wee can, like as the Queene in her solace &amp; comfort. He sayd, take away the table, for I may no longer abide, then the Knight at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the king, tooke vp the table and thanked them al, &amp; the king went hastily vnto the Castle, sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching whether the queen were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or not. And in the meane while the Queene went vp by her priuie way, &amp; put off her vppermost Vestures, and the king found her in the same cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:178576:78"/> that hee left her afore. When as the King was entred and found her, he embraced and kissed her, and sayd vnto her, this day haue I eaten with my Knight and with his Loue that is come out of his Countrey, and sithence I was borne vnto this day, mine eyes haue not seene two so like creatures in all things, as shee is to you, and this meat time I haue been so much stirred with diuers thinges, that I could no longer abide there, but that I must come &amp; search whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye were here or there: then said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Queene, sir how might you think that, for ye know well that this Tower is fast, stronge ynough, and that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die can come in nor out without you, for ye alone haue alwayes the keyes, how were it then possible for me to be there? ye find sometime one man like another, and therefore ye should take some Arguments of misdeeming or of suspition, as of late you did of the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:78"/> Ring. The King said, that is true, &amp; therefore I knowledge my selfe guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that I haue misdeemed you. After that came to him the knight and said, My Lord, I haue of long time serued your good Grace, and now it is time that I returne againe vnto mine own countrey, and therfore for all the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that I haue done vnto you, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire of you but one thing to doe for me, that is, that you noble Grace will do me such honor, as to giue vnto me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Priest, with your own hand, in the face of the Church, my Loue, whome I intend to wed, who hath followed me out of farre Countreis, and whome I shall bring thither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as my lawfull Wife, the which thing will be vnto mee great honour and worshippe when I shall come into mine owne Country. The King answered, that petition and more if you desire it of me, will I gladly doe and fulfill. Then the Knight prefixed
<pb facs="tcp:178576:79"/> the day of Marriage, at which day this good King came to the Church honourably. The Priest was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and stood adorned with his vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for to solemnize the Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. The Knight had alredy appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled the queene in his owne house, after his Country manner, and had ordayned two knightes for to leade her to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Church, they beleeuing that it had been his Paramour: and when they were in the face of the Church, the Priest sayd, who shall giue this woman vnto this knight, then the king sayd, I shall giue her to mine owne knight, and tooke her by the hand and sayde vnto her, O good woman, you are much like vnto my Queene, and therefore I loue you the better, and also for that you bee my knights Wife, and shall bee of my house, and so put the Queenes hand into the knights hand: and the Priest after the maner of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:178576:79"/> bound &amp; wedded them together. And when all this was finished and done, the Knight sayd vnto the King, Sir, my shippe that I intend to goe in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Country, is all readie to make sayle, wherefore I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech your most noble Grace, that it will please you for to accompany my wife thereunto, and that ye will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertise and informe her to loue mee, and haue me in fauor aboue all other creatures liuing, &amp; the rather for your good exhortation &amp; doctrine. Then the King with a great multitude of people went with them, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied them vnto the ship: of whose departing to the ship, many of them were sorrowfull. The King began to say vnto the Queene, my most deere friend, hearken now well vnto my councell and follow it, for it shall bee for your profit: my knight hath now heere wedded and done to you all the worshippe that in him his, wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:178576:80"/> looke that ye loue and honour him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all earthly creatures, as God hath commaunded, and that ye be to him true &amp; obedient, and as this was said, he deliuered her vnto the Knight saying, My blessing goe with you both, and our Lord keepe and conduct you in safetie to your Country. Then the Knight and the Queene bowed and inclined downe their heads to the King, and thanked him of all things, and they committed him to God, and entred into the Ship, and the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners hoisted vp their sailes, and sailed forth afore the wind, so that within a short time the King had lost y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sight of the Ship, and from thence he went hastily to the Castle, and missed the Queene, and when he found her not, he was mooued in all the parts of his body, and sought all about the tower and searched till at the last hee found the hole of the secret waye that the knight had made, and as he saw that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:80"/> hee weeping bitterly cryed out &amp; said, Alas, alas, this Knight in whome I had so great confidence and trust, hath taken away my Wife, was I not a foole, that I gaue more faith vnto his wordes, than I did to mine owne eyes. Then sayd the Empresse My Lord, haue yee vnderstood what I haue sayd, the Emperor sayd, well, in the best wise. Then sayd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse, remember how that he trusted the Knight, and yet hee deceiued him: In the same maner wise ye haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the Seuen wise Masters &amp; they labour for to destroye mee that am your Wife, and ye giue more faith vnto their words, than you doe vnto your owne eyes, for you haue well seen how your son rent and scratched mee, wherefore yet I beare and haue the tokens and markes as yee may see, and also know well how that your accursed sonne hath shamed me, and yee marke not how they defend
<pb facs="tcp:178576:81"/> him in this folly &amp; falshood, therefore it is to be dread, that it shall happen to you as it did to a king of whome to you I haue spoken. The Emperor sayd, I beleeue mine eye better than their wordes, and therefore I say to you, that to morrow I shall do iustice on him: the next day the Emperour commaunded that his Son should be hanged. Then began againe a great noyse and bewayling amongst the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people for the death of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours onely Son. At last when the Maister heard and perceiued that, he ran to the Officers which led him to the gallowes, and said vnto them, my deere friends. I pray you make not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great hast, for I thinke this day with the grace of God to saue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him from perill: and from thence the Maister hasted him towards the Emrerours Pallace, and reuerenced him according to his dutie: but the Emperour with great malice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation
<pb facs="tcp:178576:81"/> answered to him. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more haue ye ioy nor health, for that ye haue sent my son home vntaught and dumme, whome I deliuered vnto you well speaking, therefore shall you all be hanged with him: the Maister answered, Sir, the time is not long betwixt this and to morrow noone, then by the grace of God, you shall heare him well and wisely spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and vnto you the troth saying, and that I promise you vpon paine of my life (if you will spare him so long) if you find it not so. Then sayd the Emperor, if I might heare my sonne speake, it shall suffice mee, I would desire not longer to liue. Then the Maister sayd, ye shall see and heare al this, if ye will abide this little time, and then shall the dissention be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne and the strife that hath beene betwixt vs and the Empresse, and then it shall be ended. And if that ye doe not call againe your sonne, but
<pb facs="tcp:178576:82"/> put him to death for your Wiues wordes, it shall happen to you worse than it did to a Knight that died for a little bloud that hee sawe his Wife bleed, to whome after she was most vnnaturall. Then said the Emperor, that example would I faine heare. Then said the Master, let your Son bee called againe, and I shall tell you so notable an example, that during your life, ye may beware of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vntruth and vnstedfastnesse of women. Then the Emperor said, I shall goe call my Sonne againe vpon condition that to morrow I shall heare my son speake, as you haue promised me: the maister sayd, doe that my Lord, for it shall so be, and began to tell as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of the Seauenth Maister.</head>
               <p>THere was a Knight that had a faire young Wife, whome he loued entirely, insomuch that hee could not be out of her sight. It
<pb facs="tcp:178576:82"/> happened on a time that they played together at Chesse, and the Knight by chaunce held a knife in his hand, and shee playing, fortuned to smite her hand on the knife, that a little blood began to appeare. When the Knight saw that his Wife bled, he sorrowed much, &amp; was sore affrayd of his Wife, that he fel to the ground in aswound, his wife cast cold water vppon his visage, that he came a little againe to himselfe and sayd lightly, call the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with holy sacrament, for I must die: for the blood that I haue seene come out of your finger, hath smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten death to my heart, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Priest came and comforted him. And anon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee dyed without any tarrying, for whose Death, there was made great sorrow and bewaylings, and specially of his Wife, and after that the Obsequies were finished and doe accordingly, shee went and lay vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Graue, and there made the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:83"/> greatest sorrow in the world, and said she should neuer depart from thence, but as a Turtle done she wold for the loue of her husband there abide, and die: then went her Friends vnto her and sayd, what auayleth this for his soule, to liue and die heare, it is better that you goe to your house and giue Almes for the loue of God, and that shall more auaile your soule, than in this place to abide. To whom she an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered be still, yee are euill Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, consider ye not how I am from him seperated and departed by death for a litle bloud that he saw come out of my hand or finger? and therefore I shall neuer from hence depart. Her Friends hearing that, made a little house or lodging nigh vnto the graue, and put therein all thinges that to her was necessarie, and went their wayes, thinking that within a while she should be wearie to bee alone, and so desolate from all companie, that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:83"/> thereby shee should desire againe the companie of people. In the Citie was there a Law, that if a trespasser, or an offender against the Law were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the Sheriffe all the night should watch and keepe the bodye armed: and if it hapned that the bodye of him hanged were stolled away, the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe should lose his Land, and his life at the kings pleasure. It happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned soone after that the Knight was dead, a man should be hanged for trespasse that he had done, so that the Sheriffe after the Law of the land, al the night watched by the Gallowes, that was not far from the Citie, and the Churchyard was not far from the same: then began the Sheriffe to bee so cold, that hee wist not but to die for cold, except that hee might speedily warme him, it was so feruent cold, and so strong a frost: and by chaunce hee beholding from thence about him and spying a fier in the Churchyard,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:84"/> hasted him and came thereto, &amp; when he was come, hee called and knocked at the little house: the woman spake and sayd, who is that, that at this time knocketh at the house of this sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull woman, I am the Sheriffe that so much suffereth, that without anon yee let me in, I shall freeze to death, shee sayd, I feare that if I let you in, ye should shew me such words that should cause mee to be more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uier, and he sayd, I promise vnto you that I shall say no wordes to your displeasure, then shee let him in, and when hee a while had sitten by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and was well warmed, hee sayd to her, O faire woman, with your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence would I fayne speake but one word vnto you. Shee answered to him, Sir, say what it pleaseth you: he said, O Ladie, you be a faire Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, rich, and young, were it not better and more conuenient for you to dwell at home in your house
<pb facs="tcp:178576:84"/> and to giue almes, that to wast and consume your life here with weeping and crying? she said, Sir knight, had I knowne this before, you had not come herein, for I say to you, as I haue sayd to other oftentimes, you know well, that my Husband loued me so well, that for a little bloud that he saw me bleed on one of my fingers hee is dead, wherefore I shall heere die for the loue of him: as the Knight heard this, hee tooke leaue and went to the gallowes, &amp; whē he was there come, he saw that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> theefe that he left there hanging was stollen &amp; carryed away &amp; began therefore to waxe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie &amp; fell for sorrow &amp; said, woe is me what shall I doe, for I haue lost my life and all my goods? and hee going thus full of sorow and heauines, wist not which way to turne him, or to goe, at the last hee bethought him to goe to that deuout &amp; desolate Ladie, &amp; shew vnto her the heauinesse of his
<pb facs="tcp:178576:85"/> heare, to wit, if she could giue him any good counsell, And when he was thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come, he called, and she asked the cause of his knocking: then sayd hee, Madame, I am the Sheriffe that was right now with you, &amp; I wold faine shewe you the secrets of my heart, therefore I pray you for the loue of God open the doore: &amp; he wēt in the sayd to her, O most vertuous Ladie, I am come to haue your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell and aduise, for you know well the Lawes of the Land are, that whenso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer any man is hanged &amp; stolne from off the Gallowes, then the Sheriffes life and goods be in the kings hands. Now it happened in the time that I was here with you and warmed me, the theefe is stollen from y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Gallows, therefore I pray you for the loue of God, giue me your aduise what is best to doe: she answered I haue compas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion vpon you, for by the Law ye haue lost your life and goods to the King.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:85"/> Doe now after my Councel, &amp; ye shal neither lose life nor goods: he answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, therefore I am to you greatly bound, hoping to haue good comfort: she sayd, wil you then promise to take me to your Wife? the knight answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, would God that ye were indeed so minded, but I feare least ye would disdayne so much to humble you vnto me that am so poore a knight, she said I giue you my will thereto, &amp; he gaue her againe his will, and consented to be her Knight during his life. Then sayd shee, you know well that such a day my Lord was buried, which for the loue of me dyed: take him out of his Sepulchre, and doe hang him vp in stead of the theefe. The Knight answered, Ladie your Counsaile is good. Then went they together and opened the graue and drewe him out. The Knight sayd, how shall we now doe, because ere the Theefe was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, two of his vpper Teeth were
<pb facs="tcp:178576:86"/> smitten out, and I feare me, if that were perceiued, I should die y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> death. She sayd to him, Take a stone and strike out two of his teeth, the knight answered, Madame, that may I not doe, for while hee liued, hee was my welbeloued fellow, and it should be to me a great rebuke, if I shold comēt to doe so disloyall a deed vnto his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die being dead: shee answered, for your loue shall I do it, &amp; tooke a stone and smote out ii. of his teeth, and said to the Sheriffe, take him &amp; hang him vpon the Gallowes like to the theefe. The Knight sayd, I feare me to do it for the Theefe in taking of him, was wounded vpon his head, and lacked both his Eares. And therefore if it were searched and found otherwise, it should be to my vtter vndoing.</p>
               <p>Then said she, take out your sword and make him a great wound vppon his head, and cut off his Eares. O Madam, God forbid that I doe so to
<pb facs="tcp:178576:86"/> the dead bodie that I loued so well in his life. Then sayd shee, giue mee your sword, and I shall for the loue of you doe it, &amp; tooke the sword, &amp; smote a manly stroake vpon the dead mans forehead, and cut off both his eares: and when he had thus done, she sayd, Now take and hange him, without companye, and then the Knight an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered yet I feare to hange him, for the theefe wanted both his Stones, and if that he were searched &amp; found without, all our labour were in vain: then sayd she, I saw neuer so feareful a man seeing the matter so cleare and sure, take a knife &amp; cut off his stones, and hee answered, that I may not doe in any wise, and therefore I pray you spare mee, for you know well what a man is without his Stones. She sayd for the loue of you I shall doe it, and tooke the knife in her hand and cut out her husbands stones, and said to him: Now take the Churle,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:87"/> thus disfigured, &amp; hang him vp with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dread: and they went both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and hung the body vpon the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and so was the Sheriffe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered of the kings danger. Then said the Ladie, now ye be quite of all your daungers, and deliuered from all sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes by my Counsaile, and therfore I will that ye wed mee in the face of the Church: the Knight said, I haue made a vowe that I shall neuer wed other so long as ye liue, which I shall hold: but afterward he sayd, O thou most shamefull and worst woman of all women, who would take thee to his Wife? An honourable and a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Knight was thy Husband, who for a little bloud that hee sawe of thy finger shedde, died. Now hast thou smitten out 2. of his Teeth, thou hast cut off his eares and his stones, &amp; thou hast made him a great wound in his head, what Diuell would wed thee? and therefore thou shalt neuer
<pb facs="tcp:178576:87"/> shame good man more, I shall ridde thee, and drew his sword, and with one stroke he smote off her head. The Maister sayd, my Lord, haue ye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood what I haue sayd: the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayd, right well. Amongst all women this was the worst, and the Knight rewarded her accordingly, so that she should no more men shame: &amp; the Emperor sayd moreouer, O my good Master might I once heare my sonne speake, I should haue no care of my life, Then sayd the Maister, to morrow you shall heare him speake afore you, and he shall shew the troth of all the variance betwixt vs and the Empres as I hope, &amp; tooke his leaue of the Emperour and departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How that <hi>Dioclesian</hi> the Emperors Sonne complained on the Empresse: and how hee excused himselfe of her Complaint.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:88"/>
               <p>AND after that, all the Masters assembled together, &amp; tooke their Counsell how and in what manner they should bring the Child out of Prison, &amp; lead him to the Pallace, &amp; so they went to the Child there as he lay in Prison, before the mid-day, his Will and Counsell for to heare. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom the Child sayd what ye wil that shal please me, but in no wise bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie your selues how I shall answere, or what I shall say, for with ioy I shall answere all things that shall be demaunded of me. When the seauen Masters heard that, they were right glad, and clothed him in Purple, and in cloth of Gold, and two Maisters went before him, and one on his right hand, another on his left hand, and the other three followed after him, &amp; before them all went 12. men with Instruments of musick and brought him with great melodie and honour to the Pallace, and when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:178576:88"/> heard all this Melodie, hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded what is it? then it was tould him by the standers by, saying: Sir Emperor, it is your sonne which commeth before you, &amp; before all your Lords to speak and excuse himselfe of all things that are laid to his charge. The Emperor sayd, that is good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings if I might heare my son speak. And when the Child was come vnto the Pallace, he rode to his Father, &amp; sayd vnto him, Haile my deere &amp; most Royall Father. And when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror heard the voice of his Son, hee was so glad, that for ioy he fell down to the earth, but the Child took him vp againe, and when he was come to himselfe, thē began the son for to shew his matter, and there came so great a multitude of people, and the ioy &amp; noyse of them was so great that the Child could not be heard. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour considering that, let Monney to bee cast vppon the Streets, that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:89"/> the people therwith should be occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and auoyded out of the Pallaice, that they might the better heare the Child speake, but the folke tooke no regard at al after the money. The Emperour perceiuing that, made to bee commaunded silence vppon paine of their liues, and when they were all still, the Child began to say, O most dere Father, before that I any thing say, I beseech and pray you, that the Empresse with all her Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maydens may come and be present, &amp; the Emperor commanded the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres with all her Chambermaides to come without stay: she being in great feare came with all her maides, &amp; the Child commaunded them to stand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the people in a row, that he might see them: then sayd the Child sir, lift vp your eyes, and behold the Chambermaid that there standeth in greene clothing, whom ye know the Empresse loueth best aboue all other,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:89"/> whome commaund yee to be vncloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vnto her naked body afore vs al, to see what she is: the Emperour said my deere Son in should shame vs all a woman to stand naked before vs: he sayd, if it be a woman it is my shame, and if not, let the shame abide in her. When she was vncloathed, they sayd all it was a man, and so it appeared in the nether parts, whereat greatly they woondred.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Declaration of the complaint of the Emperors Sonne on the Empresse.</head>
               <p>THen said the Sonne vnto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Behold this Ribaud hath many a night lyen with your Wife in your Chamber in adultery, and hath defiled your bed, and therefore the Empresse loued him so well, the which you knew not.</p>
               <p>When the Emperour saw that, he was impatient and wroth, so that he commaunded that she with the Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baude should be burnt: the Son sayd,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:90"/> Lord father make no hast of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before I haue reprooued her of that crime she layd vppon me falsely, and that I haue declared how shee vntruly &amp; falsely hath complayned &amp; lyed vpon mee: then sayd the Father, my deere son I commit all the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into your hands. The Sonne answered, if she be found false &amp; a lyer the law shall iudge her: but my deere Father, when ye sent after mee at the instance of her, then I with my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters beheld the stars in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> firmament and there wee saw, that if I should speak any words within seuen daies, I should haue died a shamefull death, and therefore that was the cause I spake not. And where the Empresse sayd, and put vnto me that I should haue oppressed and rauished her, shee lyeth falsely, but shee did her best for to haue caused mee to doe it. And when shee in no wise could bring mee thereto, she tooke me paper, pen, and
<pb facs="tcp:178576:90"/> inke, and bad me write the cause that I refused her, and when that I had written that I would not do or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit such great and abhominable sin, and would not my Fathers Orchard defile, then beganne shee to teare her cloathes and scratch her visage, that it ran with blood, &amp; cryed with a loud voyce, and layd vnto me the crime, and blame. When the Emperor hard this, hee beheld her with a fell coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, &amp; sayd to her in this manner, O thou wretched woman, was it not sufficient to fulfill thy foule and leacherous appetite, thou and thy Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baud, but wouldest also haue had my son? Then fel the Empres to the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours feet, and she cryed him mercy: the Emperour said, O thou cursed &amp; most vnhappy woman, thou askest forgiuenesse, &amp; thou hast deserued to die in three manner of wayes. The first is, that thou hast done adulterie: the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:91"/> seconde is, that thou hast prouoked and stirred my Sonne to sinne, and hast to him imputed and layd the crime falsely and vntruely: and the thirde, that thou hast euerie day en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tised and prouoked me with thy false tales to put him to death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law shall haue his course on thee, and iudge thee vnto death. Thē sayd the Son, Father ye know well that for the leasing that she laied vpō mee, I was dayly led vnto hanging, but my Maisters with the helpe of God hath deliuered me. O my most honourable Father, it was sayd vnto you by the Empresse y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I would also by the helpe of my Maisters depose you out of your Empire, and that I laboured to destroy you, and to set my selfe in your place, should not yee then haue sorrowed? You haue the Empire to gouerne, and wherefore should I not helpe you my most deere Father? for from you I haue my ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:91"/> and I shall hold and repute you for my soueraigne Lord and Father during the terme of my life, and I wil not in any māner depriue you of your honour, but I shall labour and busie my selfe about the gouernance of the same, and all your commaundements I shall fulfill in euery thing: but it is in like wise as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Father that cast his Son into the sea for to drowne him because he sayd that hee in time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming should be his Lord, and yet the Son by the helpe of God was saued and was made a greater Lord than he was, and yet was no hinderance to the Father, but profit, also ye shold see &amp; remember that my life &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce shall neuer hinder you, but it shall bee to your great solace and ioy. Then sayd the Emperour, blessed be almightie God, and the houre that I euer begat you, and deserued to haue such a Son that I finde so wise and good in all things: tell me now an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:92"/> by the which I may perfectly vnderstand thy wisdome, and that mine heart may the better ioy in thee. Then said the Son, first commaund silence to your people, that I bee not letted in my wordes till that I haue done: and when that is ended, giue Sentence with righteousnesse of the law vpon me, and vpon the Empres. Then commaunded the Emperor si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and the Childe began to tell in manner as hereafter followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Example of <hi>Dioclesian</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Sonne.</head>
               <p>THere was a Knight which had but one Son that he loued right derely in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning, as ye now all onely haue loued mee, whome hee deliuered to a Maister of farre coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis, to norish and to learne: the child waxed wise, and profited much, and grew as well in learning as in bodie, &amp; when hee had dwelt with his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster vii. yeres, his father desired to see
<pb facs="tcp:178576:92"/> him, and sent Letters to him that he should come againe into his Country and visit his friends, in like wise as ye haue send for me. The Child was obedient to his Father, &amp; came at his commaundenent, at whose comming hee ioyed much, for that hee was as well growne in his members, as in Doctrine, to euerie man he appeared pleasant and gentle. It happened vpon a day, that the Father and the Mother sitting at the table, and the Childe seruing them, a Nightingale came flying afore the window where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they sate, &amp; began to sing so sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they maruailed, &amp; the Knight sayd, O how sweetly this bird sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, well were him that could vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand his song, &amp; could shew the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation thereof: then the Son said, My worshipfull Father, the song of the Nightingale I could well declare but I feare your displeasure. The Father sayd, say boldly my Sonne
<pb facs="tcp:178576:93"/> the interpretatation of the bird, &amp; thē ye shall proue whether I shall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry or not, but I shall marke well the reason of mine anger: and when the son heard that, he sayd, the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale had sayd in his song, that I shall become a great Lord that shallbe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and worshipped of all men, &amp; namely of my Father, the which shall bring water for to wash my handes, and my mother shall hold the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. The Father sayd, thou shalt neuer see the day such seruice of vs to haue, nor none such dignitie shall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee, and in great malice and woodnesse, hee tooke his son vpon his shoulder, and ran to the Sea, and cast him in and sayd, lye there the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of the birds song. The Child could swim, and swimmed to a Land where he was Foure dayes without meate or drinke: the fift day there came a ship sayling, and as the Child saw that, hee called vnto the shipmen
<pb facs="tcp:178576:93"/> and sayd, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> loue of God deliuer me from the perill of Death, the shipmen sawe that it was a faire young man, they had compassion on him, &amp; went with their boate and fet him aboord, &amp; into far Countreys with them they led him, &amp; sold him there to a Duke. The Child grewe goodly and sayre, and the Duke loued him much, and had him greatly in his fauour. Vpon a time the king of that Realm let call an assembly of all the great Lords &amp; Noble men of his Land to a generall Councell. This Duke prepared and ordayned him to go to the Counsell, &amp; marked the wit and wisdome of the Child, and took the Child with him. And when they were all gathered &amp; assembled before the king in his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, My welbeloued Lords &amp; friends sayd the king, will yee wit the cause wherefore that I haue called you to this Counsell? then sayd they all, we be all (soueraigne Lord) at your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.
<pb facs="tcp:178576:94"/> Then the King sayd, it is a secret matter that I shall shew you, if that any man can open it, and declare what it signifieth, I sweare &amp; promise vnto him by my crowne, that I will giue to him mine only daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in mariage, and he shall be my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in my Realme during my life, and after my death he shall haue and possesse all my whole kingdome: and the mysterie of the Counsell is this: three Rauens still follow mee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer that I goe, they leaue me not, but cry with such horrible voices that it is great paine for me to heare them, and to behold their lookes, therefore if there bee any man which knoweth the cause of their following, and can shewe what they meane by their cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and voyd them away from mee, without doubt I shall fullfill this promise that I haue made. And as the King had thus sayd, there was none found in all the Counsaile that
<pb facs="tcp:178576:94"/> vnderstood the cause, or could mooue or put away the Rauens. Then said the Child vnto the Duke, My Lord thinke you that the King will hould his promise, if I accomplish his will and desire. Then the Duke sayd, I think he will performe what he hath promised, but will ye that I giue the King knowledge of you what ye can doe? Then the Child said, I will my life set in pledge, and I shall performe and make it good what I haue sayd. When the Duke heard that, he went to the King and sayd. My Lord the King, here is a young man that is right cunning and wise, the which promiseth for to satisfie and fulfill in all thinges your desire as touching the Rauens, if you will fulfill that which you haue promised: the King sware by the Crowne of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that which I haue promised in all thinges shall be fulfilled. Then brought hee the Childe before the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:95"/> king, and when the king saw him, he spake vnto him, O faire Child, can ye giue answere to my Question? the Child sayd, yea my Lord in the best wise. Your question, wherefore that the Rauens follow you, and horribly call vpon you, I answere thereto: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a time it happened two Rauens a Male &amp; a Female, had brought forth betweene them the third Rauen, and in that place was so great Famine, and scarcitie of all manner of things, that men, beasts and fowles died, and perished for default. The third Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that time being young in the nest, the Mother left it, seeking where she might best get her liuing, and came no more to the neast: the male Rauen seeing that, with great penurie and labour fed the yong Rauen til he was able to flye, and when the deere time was past and gone, then the Female Rauen cam againe to the young Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and would hold fellowship and
<pb facs="tcp:178576:95"/> companie with him: and as the male Rauen saw that, hee would haue dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen her away, saying thus, that shee in his great miserie and necessitie left him and his companie, and therefore now shee should want his companie and fellowship. She alleaged and sayd, that shee had in his birth great labour and sorrow, and suffered pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie, and therefore of his comapnie she should rather ioy than the Father. For this my Soueraigne Lord they follow you, asking right Iudgement which of them both shall haue the young Rauen in their companie, and this is the cause of their horrible cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and noyse that they make daily vppon you. But my Lord had you hereupon a right wise sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, you should neuer more see them or be troubled with their crying. Then sayd the king, because that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath left and forsaken the young Rauen in his most necessitie, it stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:178576:96"/> with reason and Iustice, that she shall want &amp; be without his fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship: and where she saith, that in the bearing and birth of him, shee had great paine &amp; trauell, that helpeth her not, for the paine was turned into ioy as soon as she saw the young Rauen in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world. But for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the Male is the cause of production and generation in euerie beast, &amp; also because the young rauen in his necessitie was sustained &amp; fed into the recouering &amp; norishing of his bodie, by the male, therfore I giue for a Iudgement and a sentence diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue, that the young rauen shal abide &amp; hold company with the Father, nad not with the Mother. And when the rauens heard this sentēce, with great noyse &amp; cry they flew vp into the aire, and were no more seen or found in all that region. When this was done the King demanded of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yong man what his name was? he answered, I am called <hi>Alexander,</hi> then sayd the King
<pb facs="tcp:178576:96"/> I will haue one thing of you, that ye from henceforth shall name and take me, and none other for your Father, for you shall marrie my Daughter, &amp; ye shall be possessor of all my Relame. The young <hi>Alexander</hi> abode &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led still there with the king, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man had to him fauour and loue, for he began to haunt &amp; exercise him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe in Iusts and Turneys, wherein at all time he had the prize aboue all other that were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> so that his Peere or like was not found, &amp; there was not so hard nor so obscure a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion put vnot him, but that hee could assoyle it. At that time there was an Emperour named <hi>Tytus,</hi> that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in gentlenesse, courtesie, and cruio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of all other Emperors, Kings, &amp; Princes in the world, insomuch that such fame and noise flew and ran ouer the world of it, that whatsoeuer hee was that would profite in cunning, manners, or behauiour, that he shold
<pb facs="tcp:178576:97"/> go to the Emperors court. And when <hi>Alexander</hi> heard that, hee sayd to the king, my most honourable Father &amp; Lord, ye wote well the world is full of fame of the Emperor, that it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable to abide &amp; dwell in his court, wherefore if it please you my Lorde and Father, I would gladly go to his court, that I might be wiser &amp; prōp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in manners and behauiour than I am. Whereupon answeared the King, it pleaseth me right well, but I would that yee take with you plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Gold and Siluer and other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessaries so much that ye mine honour there may saue, and that ye may haue also that is to you requisite and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie. And also me seemeth it were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient that before your departing you should marie my Daughter.</p>
               <p>Then answered <hi>Alexander,</hi> will it please you my Lord to spare mee at this time, and at my comming home againe, I shall wed her with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb facs="tcp:178576:97"/> as vnto her appertained. The King answered, sithen it is your will to goe vnto the Emperors Court, I licence you, and thereto I consent. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> tooke leaue of the King, and tooke with him of Treasure aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and then hee went to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Court, &amp; when he was come with a faire companie, hee went afore the Emperor, &amp; fell vpon his knees, &amp; saluted him, and did him reuerence. The Emperor rose vp from his seat imperiall and kissed him, and asked him of whence, and what hee was, and wherefore hee was come? he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered &amp; sayd, I am Son &amp; Heire to the King of Egipt, and am come to doe seruice to your most high Maiestie, if it please you to accept of mee. The Emperour sayd that hee was right welcome, and committed him to his Steward, and made him his caruer. The Steward ordayned him a faire Chamber, &amp; prouided him all things
<pb facs="tcp:178576:98"/> that were necessarie to the same, and <hi>Alexander</hi> behaued himselfe so well, that in short time he was beloued of all people.</p>
               <p>Not long after that, came the kings Sonne of France to doe seruice to the Emperor, &amp; to learne nurture, him the Emperour receiued honourably, and demaunded his name, and of what kindred he was come? hee answered I am Sonne to the King of France, I haue to name <hi>Lodowike</hi> your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. Then said the emperor, I haue made <hi>Alexander</hi> my Caruer, &amp; ye shall be my Cupbearer that alway ye shall do seruice afore me at my Table: and commanded his Steward to assigne him a lodging, whome he placed with <hi>Alexander</hi> in his Chamber: these were so like in stature, in visage, &amp; in condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that vnneth the one might be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> discerned from the other, but that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lexander</hi> was more cunninger in all his deedes, than was <hi>Lodowike</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:98"/> for he was a Feminine man &amp; shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast, and these two young men loued well together.</p>
               <p>The Emperour had one onely Daughter named <hi>Florentine,</hi> she was right faire and gratious and should be his Heire, whome he loued entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, shee had a Court by her selfe and Seruants to her assigned; to her the Emperour euerie day was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to send from his Table of his dainties in token of loue, by <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der:</hi> insomuch that the Daughter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to haue him maruailously in her fauour, because of his wisedome &amp; gracious behauiour. It happened vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a day <hi>Alexander</hi> at meate time had such businesse, that he serued not at the Table, nor none other gaue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance for him in his rowme: <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike</hi> perceiuing that, serued in his roome, &amp; as he had serued the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his last seruice on his knee, the Emperor commanded him to beare a
<pb facs="tcp:178576:99"/> dish to his daughter as he was wont to doe, thinking him to bee <hi>Alexander:</hi> then tooke <hi>Lodowike</hi> the dish &amp; went to the Pallace of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperors daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and saluted her with great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and set the meat before her, but till that time he had not seene her: she perceiued anon that he was not <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and sayd to him on this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what is your name, &amp; whose son are ye? he answered to her and sayd, Madame, I am the Kinges Sonne of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> &amp; my name is <hi>Lodowike</hi> shee sayd, I thanke you of your labor. &amp; he tooke his leaue &amp; departed: in the meane time came <hi>Alexander</hi> to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; they fulfilled their seruice. The Dinner done, anon <hi>Lodowike</hi> went to his bed sore sick, and <hi>Alexander</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that, went to his Chamber, and sayd to him. O my best beloued Freend and fellow <hi>Lodowike,</hi> howe is it with you, and what is the Cause of your infirmitie? Hee answeared
<pb facs="tcp:178576:99"/> him and sayd, the cause I knowe not, but I feele me so sicke that I feare me I cannot escape the death: <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> sayd, the cause of your infirmitie &amp; disease I know well, for to day as yee did beare the meat to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Daughter, ye beeheld her visage &amp; beautie so feruently, that your heart is taken and rauished with her loue. Whereupon he answered, O <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> all the Phisitions in the world could not more truely iudge my sicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, but I feare it will be my death. Then said <hi>Alexander,</hi> be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and I shall helpe you vnto my power, and went vnto the Market, &amp; bought with his own money a faire Cloth set with precious Stones, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing to <hi>Lodowike,</hi> and presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it in his behalfe vnto the mayden. As she saw that, she asked him where he had that costly and precious cloth? and hee sayd, Madame, of the sonne of the most Christian King, who
<pb facs="tcp:178576:100"/> sendeth it vnto you, for your loue, for he, but for one sight that hee hath had of you, is so sicke that hee lyeth vppon his bed vnto the death, and therefore if ye suffer him to perish, yee shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer recouer againe your honour.</p>
               <p>Then sayd she, O good <hi>Alexander,</hi> would you thus counsaile me that I should so loose my virginitie? god de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that, and bee yee sure <hi>Alexander</hi> that of such messuages yee shall neuer more winne thankes of me, therefore goe ye out of my sight, and speake no more thereof to me.: when <hi>Alexander</hi> heard that, hee did obeysance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. The next daye <hi>Alexander</hi> went againe to the Citie, and bought a Chaplet that was two times more in value than the Cloth, &amp; therewith he went to the maidens chamber and gaue it to her on the behalfe of <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike.</hi> And when shee saw that costly gift, she said vnto him in this manner: I maruaile of you, that so oftentimes
<pb facs="tcp:178576:100"/> as you haue seene and spoken with me, that you haue not done your own errand in speaking for your selfe, but for another. Then answered he, O Madame, I haue not beene so dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed because my birth is not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with yours, and also it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee neuer such a case, that my heart was so wounded, and hee that hath a good fellowe, is bound for to do him good and true fellowship, and therefore most excellent Princesse, of your most aboundant pitie haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion on him, and make him whole that you haue so sore wounded to the death, that it be not for euer layd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your crueltie and hardnes of heart. She answered him, goe your way for at this time I will giue you none answeare thereof, and as hee heard that, he tooke his leaue and departed. And the thirde day hee went to the Market and bought a girdle, that was more in value and costlier than
<pb facs="tcp:178576:101"/> the Chaplet was, and presented it to her on the behalfe of <hi>Lodowike,</hi> and when she saw and beheld that so pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, she sayd vnto <hi>Alexander,</hi> say to <hi>Lodowike</hi> that he come to my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about the third houre in the night and hee shall finde the dore open: and <hi>Alexander</hi> hearing that was glad, &amp; went to his fellow and sayd, my best beloued fellow bee of good comfort, for I haue conquered the Mayden to you, and this night I shall bring you vnto her Chamber: &amp; when that was sayd, he started vp as though he was wakened out of his sleepe, &amp; was wel reuiued, and for great ioy hee was made whole: the next night folowing <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke <hi>Lodowike,</hi> &amp; brought him vnto the Chamber of the Ladie, with whome hee was in solace &amp; ioy all the night, and from that time foorth all her heart was vpon him, so that there was but one loue betwixt them both. And after that, <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:101"/> vsed oftentimes to visite her, so that it came by processe of time to the eares of the Knights of the Court, how that the Emperours Daughter was knowne by <hi>Lodowike,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired amongst themselues how that they might therewith find him, and so to take him and slay him. As <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> had knowledge thereof, hee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him to withstand them: and when the Knightes vnderstood that, they fearing <hi>Alexander,</hi> suffered his fellow for to goe in peace. <hi>Alexander</hi> many times put himselfe in ieopardie for him, hee not knowing thereof, but the Mayd knew it well. In short time after that, there came letters to <hi>Alexander,</hi> of the death of the King of Egipt, that hee should hastily come and receiue his Kingdome with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ioy, and that shewed he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to the mayden and to <hi>Lodowike,</hi> &amp; also of his departing, whereof they were sorrowfull &amp; heauie: he sayd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb facs="tcp:178576:102"/> vnto the Emperor, my most hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord, pleaseth it you for to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstande that I haue receiued Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the death of my Father, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it behooueth me to go and receiue the Kingdome, &amp; that yee will licence mee to depart, and for all benefits to mee done, I offer my selfe and all my goods, and rather then I shold by my going, any way offend or displease you my Lord, I shall forsake all my realme &amp; al that I haue in the world, &amp; abide with you still. Then said the Emperor, know yee for certaine, that of your departing I am right heauie, for yee were the best Seruant that was in al my house, but it becommeth not the Emperor to let his Seruants from their promotions or aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but sooner to promote them to higher &amp; greater honour. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe you vnto our Treasorer, and hee shall deliuer you as much gold as ye will haue, and in the name of God
<pb facs="tcp:178576:102"/> and with my blessing goe into your Countrey. And thus <hi>Alexander</hi> had leaue of the Emperour, and bad him farewel, and many of the Court were sorrowfull for his departing, for of all hee wa beloued. <hi>Lodowike</hi> with the Maiden brought him on his way well vii. miles: after that, <hi>Alexander</hi> would not suffer them to goe further, then fell they both to the ground with great sorrow, and <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke and lift them both vp againe from the earth, &amp; comforted them with faire &amp; sweete wordes &amp; sayd: O <hi>Lodowike</hi> my most best beloued fellow, I warne you that the secrets beeing betwixt you and my Ladie, yee hide and keepe them as priuily as yee may, and take good heede to all things, for I wote another shall come and be in my steed that shall enuie you of the fauour and grace that ye stand in with the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, &amp; day and night shall lie in wait to take you with a fault, and to put
<pb facs="tcp:178576:103"/> you to a rebuke: then answered <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowicke</hi> and sayd, O <hi>Alexander</hi> I shal beware as much as to me is possible, but how shall I now doe, when I want your companie? therefore one thing I shall desire of you, that yee take this Ring of mee for a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. Then sayd he, I shall for the loue of you gladly receiue the Ring, &amp; yet should I neuer without the Ring forget you, &amp; so cōmited them to God. Then they embraced ech other about the necke and kissed, and so departed from other. Not long after the kings Sonne of Spaine named <hi>Guydo,</hi> was receiued of the Emperor in the rowme and place of <hi>Alexander,</hi> to whome the Steward assigned <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> place and Chamber, the which was verie sore against the will of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowike,</hi> but hee could not amend it. <hi>Guido,</hi> seeing that <hi>Lodowike</hi> against his will had him in his fellowship, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non hee had enuie aginst him, so
<pb facs="tcp:178576:103"/>
                  <hi>Lodowike</hi> of a long time for feare of the sayd <hi>Guydo,</hi> kept him out of the companie of the Maid. Neuertheles afterward ouercome with the loue of the Mayden, sometime haunted &amp; went againe to her as hee before time had done: <hi>Guydo</hi> shortly perceiuing the same, waited so long theron, that he knew the troth, &amp; was therefore in suertie, that the Mayden was by <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowike</hi> knowne, &amp; had accompanied with her. Vpon a time it happened that the Emperour stood in his Hall, &amp; praysed <hi>Alexander</hi> of his gentlenesse and wisedome. <hi>Guydo</hi> hearing that, sayd, My Lord hee is not so much woorthie to bee commended as you weene, for hee hath been a long while a traytor in your house. Then y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour sayd, tell me how? <hi>Guydo</hi> said, yee haue but one daughter onely, the which shall be your Heire, and her <hi>Lodowike</hi> hath defiled, and lyen by, through the helpe of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and he
<pb facs="tcp:178576:104"/> goeth to her euery night as it pleaseth him. And so soone as the Emperour heard that, he was sore mooued, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be angry; &amp; it happened <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wike</hi> vppon the same time to come through the hal, and as the Emperor sawe him hee sayde, what heere I of thee thou euill &amp; vntrue body? if it be found and prooued true, thou shalt die the most shamefull death that can be deuised. <hi>Lodowike</hi> sayd, my Lord the Emperor, what is the cause? <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> answered, I say and depose heere before my lord against thee, that thou hast defiled his onely Daughter, and euerie night thou goest to her, and doest Fornication with her, and that in battell I shall prooue and make it good vppon thy body with my bodie. Then sayd <hi>Lodowike,</hi> I am inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and not infected with the crime, and falsely thou lyest vpon me, and thereupon I hold thee battell, and I trust to God thy falshood shall come
<pb facs="tcp:178576:104"/> vppon thine owne head. Then the Emperour assigned them the day of Combat. That done <hi>Lodowike</hi> went vnto the Mayden, and shewed to her the cause, &amp; the day of battell by the Emperour assigned, and in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Guydo</hi> had him accused, and sayd to her: Now it behooueth me to haue your Counsell, or else I must die, for as you know, it had not auailed mee to haue gaine-sayd the battell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out I should haue yelded my selfe gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <hi>Guydo</hi> is strong and hardy, that his like is none but <hi>Alexander,</hi> and I am feeble, and therefore it I hold the Battaile against him, I am but a dead man, &amp; so ye shall abide shame &amp; rebuke. Then said she, follow my coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle in that ye mistrust your selfe, goe hastily vnto my Father and say to him, that yee haue receiued Letters, whereby that yee are assured that the Lord your Father is sore sicke, &amp; lieth vpon his death-bed, and desireth
<pb facs="tcp:178576:105"/> to see you &amp; speake with your person, and to dispose his Kingdome and his goods before hee depart out of this life: and so desire his licence for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> loue of your Father, that you might go vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site him, and that he will prolong and lengthen the day of battell, that in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meane season you may goe and come: &amp; when ye haue obtained his licence, as hastily as you may, secretly goe to King <hi>Alexander,</hi> and when yee are come to him, take him apart and shew him the cause of your comming, and require him in this your vtter extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie that hee will helpe and saue vs. And when <hi>Lodowike</hi> had heard her counsel, it pleased him wel, and he did thereafter: his leaue gotten, &amp; longe day and respite of the battell prefixed and assigned, he departed &amp; tooke his iourney towardes the Realme of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and neuer stayd day nor night, till hee came vnto King <hi>Alexanders</hi> Castle. And when that King <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:105"/> had vnderstanding of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, he was very glad and went to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eet him, and receiued him honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and had wonder of his comming. Then said <hi>Lodowike,</hi> O my deere Lord and my best beloued friend, my life and my death is in your handes, or as ye sayd to mee before, that I should haue another fellow, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> which should lye in waite to espie me, and to destroy mee, without I looked the wiselier to my selfe: so, as long as I night, I abstained me, till I could no longer: but afterwards the Kings Sonne of <hi>Spaine</hi> made watch so long ouer me, vntill he perceiued the truth. In the end hee accused me vnto the Emperour, so that on the Eight day hereafter from this day, I must be ready &amp; prepare me to fight with him body against bodie: and as ye knowe well, he is a very strong and a hardy man, and I am weake and feeble, and therefore hath <hi>Florentine</hi> counsai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:178576:106"/> mee that I should not hide this matter from you, for she knoweth you for a faithfull Friend, and that yee would not leaue vs in this necessitie. Then said <hi>Alexander,</hi> is there any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die that knoweth of your coming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me for this matter, more then <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentine?</hi> he answered him and sayd no creature liuing, for I tooke leaue o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Emperour to go visite my Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lying grieuously sicke. Then asked <hi>Alexander</hi> him, what counsell hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Florentine</hi> giuen you, how &amp; in wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wise I might helpe you? He said, O moste constant and faithfull friend In this wise she hath counselled me, considering that we be like, that you should come and doe the battell with him, and no man shall knowe you bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> shee, and the battell done, I shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come againe to the Court, and yee t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your Country. Then he asked whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the day should be of the battaile, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he said, Eight days hence. Then sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:106"/>
                  <hi>Alexander,</hi> if I should this day tarie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen I cannot come by the day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed. Wherefore see what I shall do, I haue bidded all my Subiects, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Morrow they should come to my wedding, and if I should goe? then is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he day lost; if I go not and do y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell, then <hi>Florentine,</hi> and ye are both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndone, what thinke ye now best for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o doe? When <hi>Lodowike</hi> heard that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee fell to the earth, and began to sigh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd sorrow out of measure, saying: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrow and heauinesse come to me on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll sides. Then said <hi>Alexander</hi> vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, be of good comfort, for I shal not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orsake you after such a sort, though I should loose my life and Kingdome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut harken what I haue thought: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch that we are both like, so that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne of vs cannot be knowne from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther and we both together alike, &amp; I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m not yet greatly knowne here, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y barons &amp; other folk shall take you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r me, therefore heere shall ye abide &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178576:107"/> tarrie and marry my wife in my stea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and hold the feast and bridall, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in all things euen as though I were there my selfe present, Except when as yee come to bedde with my wife, looke that ye be there true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and I shall without tarrying go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and take my horse and ride thithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whereas the battell shall be, &amp; if god giue me the victorie that I may ouer come &amp; vanquish your enemie, I shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come againe secretly, and yee shall go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againe to your best beloued. This done, <hi>Alexander</hi> bad <hi>Lodowike</hi> fare well, and tooke his iourney toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Emperors Court for to fight an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doe the battell with <hi>Guydo,</hi> and <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dowike</hi> tarried in <hi>Egypt</hi> in the stea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of King <hi>Alexander.</hi> And vppon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> next morning early came <hi>Lodowik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as though it had been king <hi>Alexande,</hi> and there solemnely in the face of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church he espoused <hi>Alexanders</hi> wife and solemnized the marriage Fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:107"/> with great royaltie of delycates and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aintie meates, plentie of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of wines, and diuers melodies of Instruments of Musicke, and made great ioy and cheere for the noble men and all other people that were there assembled. And when the night was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome he went to bed with the Queene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd laid betweene him and her a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en Sword, whereof shee had great wounder but nothing shee sayd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hee lay with her euery nyght, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onge as <hi>Alexander</hi> was out. Then king <hi>Alexander</hi> at the day that was prefixed and set, came vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and said, O most Soueraigne Lord it is so, that I haue left my Father right sicke, Neuerthelesse I am come for to defend my Honour, and my promise to performe. The Emperor said, ye do right well, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ording to a Noble man, and fortune <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall fauour you in your iust and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eous quarrell. And when the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb facs="tcp:178576:108"/> Daughter vnderstoode that <hi>Alexander</hi> was come, anon shee sent for him, &amp; when hee was come to her, shee embraced him, and with ioy and gladnesse shee kist him, and blessed the time that shee might see him againe, &amp; demaunded of him where he had left her friend and Louer <hi>Lodowike?</hi> then hee declared vnto her all the processe, and how hee had left him King in his Realme: and so took his leaue of her, &amp; went to <hi>Lodowikes</hi> Chamber, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was no creature that thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise but it was <hi>Lodowik,</hi> onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Florentine:</hi> the next day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before <hi>Alexander</hi> went vnto the battaile, hee sayd vnto the Emperor in presence of <hi>Guydo,</hi> My most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Soueraigne Lord, this <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> hath falsely and vntruely accused mee vnto your Noble Grace, that I should bee of such acquaintance with your Daughter, that should bee vnto the dishonour of your most Noble
<pb facs="tcp:178576:108"/> person and hers, &amp; vnto that I swear and affirme by the holy Euangelists, that she was neuer in such manner of wise by me knowen, as he hath allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; infourmed to you, and that this day with the ayd and helpe of God, I shall prooue and make good vpon his bodie. Then said <hi>Guydo,</hi> yet once I say againe, and sweare by the holy Euangelists, &amp; by all that God hath made, that thou hast had knowledge &amp; hast defiled the Emperors daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that I shall make good vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thy head. Whereupon they leapt vpon their Coursers, and fircely ran together with their Speares, that they both brake and shiuered in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and then drew their swords and fought so long together, vntill at the last <hi>Alexander</hi> with great might and strength at one stroke smote off <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does</hi> head, and sent it vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Daughter, wheeeof she was right glad, and bare it to her Father,
<pb facs="tcp:178576:109"/> and said, Father, behold the head of him that you and me hath so falsely defamed. When the Emperor percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the victory, anon he sent for <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> whom he thought to haue been <hi>Lodowike</hi> and sayd: O <hi>Lodowike</hi> this day your honour and my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters yee haue saued, ye shall stand and be to morrow in my grace and fauor. and whatsoeuer he bee that hereafter shall againe defame you, hee shall for euer stand in my indignation. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> said, God helpeth &amp; saueth them that trust in him, &amp; alway wreaketh the bloud indefectiue or innocent: but nowe most vndoubted Lord, of one thing I require you: at my departing frō my father I left him sore sick, that it will like you for to licence me to goe and see how it standeth with him, and if that hee be any thing amended, I shall incontinent come againe: then the Emperour said, that pleaseth me well, but yee may in no manner wise
<pb facs="tcp:178576:109"/> leaue me, for frō henceforth I cannot be without your presence. <hi>Alexander</hi> tooke leaue of the Emperor, and bad him farewell, and rode againe to his Realme, who when <hi>Lodowike</hi> sawe, he made great cheere and gladnesse, and friendly receiued him and said, O most true friends of all friends, tel me how you haue done and sped in your iourney and businesse, and what end ye haue brought it to? then said he, go to the Emperor and serue as ye haue done before, for I haue gotten you more grace &amp; fauour of him, than euer yee had before time, and I haue also smit off the head of your greatest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my &amp; aduersary. Then said <hi>Lodowike</hi> yee haue not onely at this time saued my life, but many times heretofore, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which as yet I cannot discerne, but God reward you, and so departed: and went againe to the Emperour, and there was no man that knew of the absence of <hi>Alexander,</hi> saue onely
<pb facs="tcp:178576:110"/>
                  <hi>Lodowike.</hi> And when the night was come, hee went to bed to the Queene. and anon he had with her sweete and friendly woordes and embraced and kissed her: then said shee, you haue made this time all too long, in that ye haue shewed nothing of friendship or loue, how may this be? Then said hee, wherefore say ye that, shee sayd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie night as I was in my bed, you haue layd betwixt you &amp; mee a naked sword, and yee haue neuer tasted nor turned you towards mee more than now. And when the King heard that, he thought on the truth of his fellow, and said vnto her, O my most deere Lady and Queene, it was not done for any euill will, but for a good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and for a perpetuall loue: but she thought in her selfe, that loue shall you neuer more haue of mee, but that despight she thought I shall reuenge vpon thee. Then there was a knight that she afore had a little loue and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:178576:110"/> vnto, and shee began for to loue him more and more, so long till at the last they thought and imagined how they might destroy and slay the King, and therefore they got poyson &amp; poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned the King, so that if hee had not been right stronge of complexion, hee had dyed thereof, but it wrought in him so sore, that it cause him to be a most fowle and horrible Leaper, as euer was seene vppon the earth. The Lords the Noblemen of his realme, and the Queene also seeing this, des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pised him, and sayd that it behooued not a Leaper to raigne ouer vs, for hee should not procure nor ingender any faire or cleane heires, and so hee was deposed of his dignitie Royall, and driuen out of his Realme. In the meane time died y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Lodowike</hi> married his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and after that , <hi>Lodowikes</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dyed, so that <hi>Lodowike</hi> Raigned both Emperor, and King of <hi>Fsaunce</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178576:111"/> at once. When King <hi>Alexander</hi> heard that, he thought in himselfe, now my fellow raigneth together vppon the Empire and Realme of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to whom may I go better thā vnto him, for whom many times I haue ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my life? And vppon a night hee rose vp and made him ready, &amp; tooke with him his staffe and clapper, and went toward the Emperors country, and when he was come nigh vnto the gate, hee sat him among other lazers, expecting the giuing of the almes, and on a suddaine as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Emperor wēt out of his Pallace, all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> poore lazers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to ring their clappers, and the good king <hi>Alexander</hi> did like to the other, but there was no almes giuen to them. He tarried so long vnto the time that the Emperor was set, and serued at the table. Then went King <hi>Alexander</hi> into the gate, and knocked thereat, &amp; the Porter asked who was there? <hi>Alexander</hi> answered him, I
<pb facs="tcp:178576:111"/> am a poore despised man, but for the loue of God I require you, that you turne not your sight from my Visage, and that you will for the reward of god doe my message vnto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour he asked what is the matter? <hi>Alexander</hi> said, goe &amp; tell him here is a Lazer that is right horrible to see, the which prayeth him for the loue of god and King <hi>Alexander,</hi> that he will graunt him, this day to eat his almes before him vpon the earth in his hall. The Porter said, I wounder that ye dare desire that of my Lord? for why, all the hall is full of Lords and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, and if they behould you, they would all abhorre and leaue their meate: But for as much as you haue required mee so lamentably, for the loue of god I shall goe and doe your errand whatsoeuer happen thereof, and so he went forward and did his message vnto the Emperour. When the Emperor hard the Portername
<pb facs="tcp:178576:112"/>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the King of <hi>Egipt,</hi> he sayd to his Porter, go bring him afore me, how horrible soeuer that his Visage bee, and ordaine him a place before me that he may eate his meate and feede in my presence. The Porter brought him anon, &amp; ordained him a place and set him to meate before the Emperour: and when hee was well refreshed, hee sayd vnto one of the Emperours Seruantes, My deere friend doe mee this errand vnto the Emperour, say vnto him that I pray him for the loue of God &amp; King <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> that he will send me his Cup of wine. The seruant said, for the loue of God I shall doe it, but I beleeue it will not bee, for if yee once drinke of my Lords cup, he will no more drinke of the same, neuerthelesse hee did the errand. Anon as the Emperour heard him name King <hi>Alexander,</hi> he commaunded his Cup to bee filled of the best wine, and bare it to him, the
<pb facs="tcp:178576:112"/> which Wine when hee had receiued, he put it into his bottell, and took his Ring that <hi>Lodowike,</hi> had giuen vnto him and put it into the Cup, and sent it againe to the Emperor. And when the Emperour saw the Ring, anon he knew that it was the same that hee had giuen to <hi>Alexander</hi> in friendship when hee departed from him, and thought in his heart, that <hi>Alexāder</hi> is dead, or else this man is maruailously come to the Ring, and commaunded anon that the Lazer shold not depart till the time that he had spoken with him, for in no wise could he haue any knowledge of him, nor yet repute him for <hi>Alexander.</hi> After that the Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was done and ended, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour tooke the sicke man apart, and asked how he came by the Ring? <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> demaunded if ye knew well the Ring? The Emperour said, I know it right well. <hi>Alexander</hi> sayd, wote yee also vnto whome you haue giuen
<pb facs="tcp:178576:113"/> it? The Emperor said, I wote right well: how is it then sayd <hi>Alexander</hi> that ye know not me, for I am <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> vnto whome ye gaue the same Ring? when the Emperor heard that he fell to the ground for sorrow, &amp; tare his robes and cloathes, and with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great sighings &amp; be wailings sayd, O <hi>Alexander</hi> you are the one halfe of my Soule, where is your goodly and delicate bodie, now so vncleane and pittifully infected, that was so faire and pleasant to behold? he answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, this is happened vnto me for the great fidelitie that you haue done to mee in my bed with my Wife, when you laid a naked sword betwixt you and her: wherefore she became wroth and hated me, that she and a Knight that afore time she ought loue vnto, haue poysoned mee as you may see, and moreouer they haue driuen mee out of my Realme. And when y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror heard that, he for loue took him
<pb facs="tcp:178576:113"/> about the necke and kissed him, and said, O my most and intierly beloued Brother, I sorrow to see you in this great sicknesse and miserie, I would to god I might die for you, but my most deare friend suffer patiently a little time till that wee haue sent for all the Phisitians &amp; wise Maisters in phisick to haue their counsell and aduise, if there be any remedy or hope of recouering of your health: and if it be possible to helpe you, wee shall neither spare Empire, Lordship, nor other good temporall, to make you whole and sound. In the meane time he was brought into a faire chamber, richly hanged and appointed of all manner of things that were requisite and necessarie for his ease and health, and in all hast he sent his messengers through all parts of the world, for the most expert Phisitians that might be found, Of whome within a moneth after were come and assembled before
<pb facs="tcp:178576:114"/> the Emperour Thirtie, which were right expert &amp; skilfull in that science, to whome the Emperour sayd. My welbeloued maisters I haue a friend that is very grieuously infected with a foule Leaprosie, whome I would right faine were healed and made as sound as euer he was, sparing ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for gould ne siluer, nor all other goods whatsoeuer that I haue in all this world, but I would gladly giue it to recouer his health againe. Then answered the Maisters, all that euer is possible to be done by phisicke, you shall soone vnderstand after that wee haue seen the person: and forthwith as they sawe him and perceiued the cause of his infirmitie, they iudged the disease incurable for all the Maisters liuing. And when the Emperor heard that, he was right sorrie in his heart, and committed it vnto the helpe of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mithtie god, calling vnto him religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men and poore people, and other
<pb facs="tcp:178576:114"/> deuout persons, and desired them to pray to god, that he would vouchsafe to make whole his friend the sooner for their good deeds and prayers: and he himselfe with many other fasted &amp; prayed humbly to almighty God for the health of his friend. Vpon a day as King <hi>Alelxander</hi> was in his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, there came vnto him a voyce say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if the Emperour will with his owne hands slay his two sons which his wife hath borne him at one bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, &amp; wash thy body with the blood of them, then thy flesh shalbe as faire and as cleane as the bodies of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle chidrē. When king <hi>Alexander</hi> had heard this, he thought with himselfe, this vision is not to be shewed, for it is sore against nature that any man should slay his owne Sonne for reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of the health of a strange man. The Emperor night and day lay in his prayers with great deuotion, still ppaying to God for remedy for
<pb facs="tcp:178576:115"/> King <hi>Alexander.</hi> So that at the las<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there came a voyce vnto him &amp; sayd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how long will yee thus crye and ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon me, when it was openly shewe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto King <hi>Alexander</hi> how that he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> shold be made whole. The Empero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hearing that, went vnto <hi>Alexande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and sayd, Of all friends the best an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> most true, Blessed bee the most hig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, the which neuer fayleth them that call and trust on him: Of whom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I haue knowledge, that it is shewed vnto you, how and in what wise that ye may be made whole, wherefore I pray you that you will openly shew vnto me, that wee may ioye together, and if ye need any thing thereto that I may doe, I shall fulfill it vnto my power, yea &amp; for your health giue all that I haue to. <hi>Alexander</hi> sayd, sir I dare not shew it to you, how that I may be cured and healed of my mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, for it exceedeth, and it is a thing against nature for to be done, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:178576:115"/> I will not shew it to you, how bee it I haue great trust &amp; confidence in you. The emperor said, Alexander trust in mee, for whatsoeuer is possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for to be done for the recouering of your health, I sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hide nothing from me: then sayd <hi>Alexander,</hi> I haue of God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that if you will slay your 2. sons with your owne hands, and wash me in their bloude, It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il be whole, and therefore I haue no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hewed it vnto you, for mee think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h it is against na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the Father should slay his own children for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> health of a strange man: the Emperour sayd, say not that yee bee a strange man, for I loue you as I loue my selfe, &amp; therfore if I had Ten children, I should not spare one aliue to haue your health, After that the emperour watched and espied his time when the Empresse and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Chamberers were out of the way, and when ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was, he entered</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:178576:116"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>